<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penitent hermit, or, The fruits of jealousie being a true and witty relation of a pleasant adventure / written by a Lady to a dutchess : in two parts compleat.</title>
            <author>Lady.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27973</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13534764</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199411</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240939992</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1233</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13534764</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 471:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penitent hermit, or, The fruits of jealousie being a true and witty relation of a pleasant adventure / written by a Lady to a dutchess : in two parts compleat.</title>
                  <author>Lady.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 141 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199411:1"/>
            <p> The PENITENT HERMIT: OR, THE FRUITS OF JEALOUSIE.</p>
            <p>Being a True and Witty Relation of a pleasant Adventure writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a Lady to a Dutchess.</p>
            <p>In Two Parts Compleat.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licensed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Feb.</hi> 7. 1678/9. </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Roger L'Estrange</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the Sign of the Popes head in the new Exchange in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199411:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199411:2"/>
            <head>THE Penitent Hermit. OR <hi>The Fruits of Jealousie.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The First Part.</head>
               <p>I Shall alwayes be joyful to obey your commands, Madam, but have a double obligation at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, to perform your last, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you desire, that I should give you an exact information of all that concerns the Hermit of <hi>T.</hi> Because I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the relation of it will afford you some short divertisement. I should only wish, Madam, that the manner of writing might not lessen the beauty of the Subject; but instead of politeness
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199411:3"/> and flourish, which are Talents not to be found in this Countrey; I dare assure you, that this relation shall want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of exactness and sincerity; and hope that the commands you have laid upon me, not to omit any particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, will incline you to pardon the length of this Letter. And I doubt not, but your satisfaction will be so great to see a man of quality, in so corrupt an age as ours, by retirement and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, imitate the fervor of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Anchorites;</hi> that that alone will move you to excuse a great many escapes in the writing.</p>
               <p>You must know then, Madam, that the Hermit of <hi>T.</hi> who, for the space of a year, went by no other name, came to this Desert in the cold of Winter, in the year one thousand six hundred and seventy four, you are not ignorant that this Countrey is exceeding cold, and especially the Hilly-places, one of these he chose for his retirement, on the top of which there is a spacious grot formed by nature in a Rock, which our Hermit so ordered, that though a man could not commodiously dwell in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199411:3"/> it, yet He might live there secure From the danger of wild beasts.</p>
               <p>So soon as the people of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Villages understood that there lived a man in that Desert, they were much surprized: but their surprise turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to admiration, when they observed all the actions of the Hermit, seeing him lead a life more like an Angel than a mortal man; his Apparel was very mean, and used no other food but bread and water, buying all his bread, though it was offered him <hi>gratis:</hi> He made answer still to those that would have bestowed it on him, that it was not his intention to rob the Alms that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to those who were really poor. He never came out of his grot, but to go to the next Church, and behaved himself in that holy place with wonderful reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and devotion, the rest of the days he spent in reading, prayer, or at work, in a little Garden, which he had made over his grot. The rumour of this so extraordinary a thing, was quickly spread abroad over all the Province; so that many persons of quality came to see the Hermit. He on the other
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199411:4"/> hand with much civility told them that he preferred his sollitude, to all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that they were willing to render him, and that if he had had a purpose to have continued still in the hurry of the World, he would not have betaken himself to such a retirement: yet it was easie to be perceived, notwithstanding of his natural sweetness of disposition, that his mind lay under some violent discontent. Amongst so many, whom curosity invited to the Hermits grot, some there were who thought fit to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure that way of living; which how pure and blameless so ever, yet seemed to them unreasonable upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but because it was not in fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: they discoursed to him on that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and he received the advice with a self denied humility, thinking it enough to answer those, who took the pains to counsel him, that he besought them to examine all his actions, and to reprove him when he did amiss, that he was ready to take in good part what ever correction might be given him; but that for his manner of life, there was nothing faulty in it; and that he had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199411:4"/> not followed that course without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting those who had greater know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge than himself: that modest answer; for some time stopped the mouths of those that spoke to him on that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: but seeing the humour of such as make it their business to examine the actions of other men, give not over easily, they thought fit to urge the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to declare his true name. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that attack with the same tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity as the former; thinking it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to Answer, that it had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his opinion, that it was lawful for all men, to endeavour to procure their own happiness; and seeing the greatest good, that is to be attained, was salvation, he thought he might be suffered to work it out, without the trouble of unnecessary avocations. He told them again, that they should make it their business to reprove him, when he was guilty of any thing blame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; but that his name and quality ought to be a thing indifferent to all men.</p>
               <p>Matters were in this State, when <hi>Mounsieur de M.</hi> whose merit and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty you know, came to <hi>Terrasson:</hi> you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199411:5"/> are not ignorant, Madam, that he hath generously forsaken the World, that he may with more freedome mind his own salvation; but was obliged for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordering of his domestick affairs to to come into this place. He was no sooner come hither, but that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the wonderful life, which the Hermit lead; and though the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port made him very desirous to be known to him, yet he would not go to visit him, until he had first sent to ask his leave; our Hermit, whom the Deserts had not rendered haggard, made him such an answer as might be expected from a most accomplished person; which obliged <hi>Mounsieur de M.</hi> to wait upon him that very day; who, after an hours conversation, confessed that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met with a man of greater devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and wit: on this occasion the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit did that which he had never done before since his retirement, he repayed the visit which he had received; and all the discourse which he had then with <hi>Mounsieur de M.</hi> as well as the first time ran upon the contempt of the World, on the difficulty of working
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199411:5"/> out our salvation therein, and how the things which appear to us most inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, may become criminal, by the way that men apply themselves to them: the Hermit spake of that with so much fervency, that it was easie to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that he was convinced of the truth of what he said: and having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted his friend to confirm himself in the contempt which he testified of the World; they mutually before parting promised a constant and sincere friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: it was no hard matter to unite two hearts, which were wholly devot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the service of God, and had no other aim but the thoughts of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and seeing Charity is one of those works which are most acceptable to God, <hi>Mounsieur de M.</hi> caused a bed and some other things to be carried to the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits grot to render his abode there some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more commodious during the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Winter, which was so sharp in that Rock, that a man, who continued constantly there, was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of contracting some mortal distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: the Hermit made great difficulty to accept the present; and seemed more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199411:6"/> addicted to his own thoughts than to all the reasons that were alleadged: to bring him to a consent, but after a profound musing, well then! Good God, said he, it is just that I should preserve my miserable life, seeing how wretched so ever it be; I am to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for it to—At these words he stopt, excusing himself to those be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom he spake them: and stood so close to his guard for the future, that when he was obliged to admit of visits, it was easily perceived, that he strictly observed himself in his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Mounsieur de M.</hi> had put an end to the affairs that brought him into this Countrey, he went and took leave of his friend, offering him in his absence all the services which he might desire of him, in a place where he had absolute power: though he accepted none of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, yet he testified as much gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for them, as if he had intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have used them: at that time I was at <hi>Terrasson,</hi> and prayed <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de M.</hi> to bring me to a sight of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199411:6"/> that Hermit: he made some difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do it, because the onely favour that he had begg'd from him at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was, that he would hinder him as much as he could from being burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by needless visits: yet he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to condescend to my intreaty, and caused me to be conducted to the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits grot, who received me with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>al civility; and seeing I put no indiscreet question to him, and stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but half an hour, I gave him less trouble than most part of those that went to see him, and I was told that he appeared less disturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at my visit than he used to be; for my own part, Madam, I was so affected with what I discovered in that man, that I could not forbear to give you some account of it, and since the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which I had the honour at that time to write to you, there hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the strangest adventure that ever was.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Easter</hi> day in the year one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred and seventy six, came to <hi>Terrasson</hi> an equipage consisting of two Litters, three men on horse back,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199411:7"/> and some footmen in Livery; in one of the Litters was a Lady, who seemed to be about five and thirty years of age, and notwithstanding the paleness and melancholly of her looks, gave suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient evidence, that she had been a most lovely person; she had with her a young Maid about twelve or thirteen years old of surprising beauty, in the other Litter were some serving Maids, and all allighted at an Inn; so soon as they arrived, she, who seemed to be the Mistress of the Company, sent to intreat the Curate of <hi>Terrasson</hi> to come to her. She discoursed with him an hour in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and shed many tears during the conversation; and when the Curate took leave of her, she prayed him to come to her again next morning by six of the Clock: the night she spent in disquieting thoughts, and so soon as it was day, took her Litter, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied only with that fair young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and a man on horseback, she sent to give the Curate notice; and all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether went streight to the grot, the Hermit was still about his morning Prayers, when they knocked at the door
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199411:7"/> of his Cell; he opened it, and came out to meet those who were come to see him; but his surprise was great when at the first step he made out of his Rock he saw these two Ladies fall upon his neck, and melting in tears embrace him that action so unexpected, made him retire two steps backward, and look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him more attentively: but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can approach his amazement, when he discovered that these two were the persons in the World whom he most tenderly loved; that sight put him in so great disorder that he wanted strength to stand; so that freeing himself from the embraces of those two afflicted beauties, he went and fell on his knees hard by the door of his Cell; where lifting his eyes and hands to Heaven: O God! Cryed he, strengthen me, and let me not succumb in a conflict wherein I engage onely for thy glory, or to say better, give me power to compleat a Pennance which bears but little or no proportion to the greatness of my Crimes: having said so he held his peace; and found himself in so great an agitation of mind that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199411:8"/> he had almost fainted away; that acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which on any other occasion would have afflicted those two Ladies, wrought in them a secret joy, seeing it was a sign that he, of whom they had come in search with so much care, was not a little moved in seeing of them. They were solicitous in assisting that dear patient, who, being a little come to himself again, beheld the Lady that was by him with a countenance shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some marks of shame and confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Is it possible, Madam, said he to her; that you have still so much kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for me, after the crimes I have committed, as to incline you to expose your self to the fatigues of a tedious Journey, in the search of a wretch; or ought not I to fear, that having so just a cause of anger, you come to heap upon me reproaches, which how bitter so ever, cannot but be just. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to whom he addressed these words, by her actions gave evidence, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anger nor resentment had given any occasion to her Journey. She cast her self at the feet of the Hermit, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that she was criminal, and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199411:8"/> her imprudence had been the cause of all their misfortunes, that she saught after him to implore his pardon, and that she would never leave him, till she had obtained it. The Man, who waited on the Lady, and appeared a Person of discretion, knowing that their Conversation ought not to be publick, prayed the Company present, to withdraw a little, and to give li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to those, who had more to discourse of together, than was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to be said before witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. The conversation of the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and Lady lasted above five hours, and she had never been willing to have broken it up so soon, if she had not feared, that the young Lady, who came with her, and who was her Daughter, might be incommoded by fasting so long. When they took their leave of the Hermit, he promised to do all that lay in his power to give them the satisfaction which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired; but that he would be glad to have the rest of the day, and the whole night to resolve in: and they knowing his humour, durst not urge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199411:9"/> him further. He earnestly intreated them to go and take their repose, thinking that they needed it. And therefore they returned, praying Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to favour their Journy with a happy success. But the time of their Crosses was not as yet at a period, and their patience was still to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to more severe tryals, as you shall see in the sequel of my Discourse. The two Ladies spent that night as the former in trouble and anxiety; and so soon as it was day returned again to the Hermitage; they found the door shut, and durst not knock at first; but having waited there a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty while, they made a little noise, that they might engage him, whom they thought to be within, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; that likewise having no effect; the young Lady grew impatient; and going to the door, as she stooped to look in, she saw a paper lying at her foot, wherein were these words writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with Charcole;</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199411:9"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>IF the constraint, that I put upon my self in forsaking you, were known to your self, I am perswad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you would pity me; I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had the power to tell you, that the Pennance I have enjoyned my self, is not to end before</hi> Christmas; <hi>but seeing I cannot dispose of my self without your consent, I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to intreat a Person of great me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to take the pains to learn your sentiments. I know you are so good, that I dare hope you will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me the time, that I praefix; when that is over, I swear by all that is sacred, that I shall come to you, and spend the rest of my dayes in your Company. I need not, I think, recommend to you the care of our Children, seeing one, who has never failed in the smallest duty of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, will not be wanting in the greatest: the onely thing, which I</hi>
                              <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199411:10"/>
                              <hi>most earnestly recommend to you, is that you would have a care of your health, which is a thousand times dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to me, than my life.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>I shall not tell you, Madam, how great affliction these two lovely Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons felt, at the reading of that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; you may guess at their sorrow by the pains they took to find the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; which wrought so upon them, that they were carried back to their Lodgings rather dead than alive. Whilst they were abandoning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to grief, he that was the cause of it, took the way to a house of mine, about three leagues from <hi>Terrasson.</hi> I was not a little surprized, when one of my Servants came and told me, that the Hermit desired to speak with me in private.</p>
               <p>Having ordered him to be let in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Garden where I was, I came and received him, testifying to him my gratitude for the honour he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to do me; but he suffered me not to conclude what I intended to say.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199411:10"/> When you have well known me, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, said he, you will not retain for me the esteem wherewith you seem to honour me; I come hither to implore your assistance, on a very important occassion, seeing the interest of what is dearest to me in this world is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned: Know then, Madam, that that Hermit, whom you have taken to be a man of exemplary piety, is a Malefactor, come hither to seek a refuge, and bewail his sins in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try remote from the place where he hath committed them; I was born in <hi>Provence,</hi> of a considerable Family; yea, and I might say, that I might have enjoyed all happiness, had not jealousie set me upon actions, which can admit of no excuse. I have a Wife, who by an extraordinary good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, so far from entertaining any grudge or resentment against me, has exposed herself to the fatigues of a long and tedious Journy to come in search of me; she is at present at <hi>Terrasson,</hi> and, I believe, in extream sorrow; for having yesterday put her in hopes, that I might return home
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199411:11"/> with her, and having begg'd of her to give me some time to bring my self to a final determination, as to what I should do; I have, after more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture consideration, thought my self obliged to fulfil a vow which I have made, and which does not expire till <hi>Christmass.</hi> This morning, before I came hither, I left a Letter, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her with my resolution, and have even taken the boldness, Madam, to tell her, that I was going to pray a Person of exceeding great merit, to allow her protection in this Country, and to inform her more at length of my thoughts, which are, that if my entreaties cannot prevail upon her, you would be so good to let me know it, at the place where I shall tarry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you be pleased to send me news. Tho the Discourse which I have told you was pretty long, yet I had not the least thought of interrupting him. I was so surprized at what I heard, that I had no other thoughts but to learn a clear information of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, which seemed to me very extraordinary; but when it behoved
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199411:11"/> me to answer, I told the Hermit, that he was not mistaken, when he thought that I would be joyful to render him all kind of services; and I did what I could to incline him to give me a particular account of what he had onely told me in general: but I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that he desired not to engage on that subject. All that I could learn of him was, that he was descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of that illustrious Family of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> so famous in <hi>Provence,</hi> and that he was the Count of <hi>Freslon.</hi> After our discourse I desired him to walk in into the house, but he excused himself; so that I perceived it would have been indiscretion in me to press him any more. In all his discourse he expressed to me a great tenderness for his Lady; and therefore so soon as he was gone, I made ready to go to <hi>Terrasson:</hi> when I came there, I was conducted to the Lodgings of the Countess of <hi>Freslon,</hi> and sent to know if I might wait upon her: She thought at first, that curiosity had moved me to make that little journey, but she was not a little surprized, when I sent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199411:12"/> her word by one of her Men, that I had matters of importance to impart to her. She presently thought, by reason of the Letter, which her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had left, that it must be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what concerning him. She sent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiselle, her Daughter, to meet me, who prayed me to come up into her Chamber. I found her in bed under such grief and affliction, as might have moved the hardest heart to pity. I shall not trouble you, Madam, with a relation of all that might be said in such a Case. I exhorted her, with all the Rhetorick I had, to take pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. I shall not excuse, Madam, said she, melting in tears, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which you observe in me. There are some occasions, wherein steadfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness comes near to barbarity; and to let you know, that no person ever had so great cause of affliction, I shall not stick to tell you all that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen me, both before and since my marriage. The confidence, that Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Freslon</hi> hath reposed on you, warrants mine, when you shall be pleased to signifie to me, that you are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199411:12"/> at leasure to hear the Relation. I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured the Countess, that I was so much concerned therein, that I should be alwayes extreamly satisfied to be informed of her affairs; but that I thought it, before all other things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, that she should leave a place, where she could not but be wery much incommoded. I offered her the use of my house. She thanked me for the favour, but, I believe, would not have accepted it, if I had not told her, to make her consent, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps her Husband might let me hear from him again. This last reason prevailed more with her than all the rest. I resolved not to leave her, but to have her with me. She left all her Equipage in the place where she was; and having come into my Coach, with the young Lady her Daughter, and two Maids to attend them, they came with me to my house. By the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course which we had together, I found, that that <hi>Provencial</hi> Countess was very wity: and I was not willing that even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to engage her in the Relation of her Adventures; for seeing I am not so
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199411:13"/> curious as the Heroins of Romances, I had rather sup and go to rest, than spend the night in hearing a Story. Next morning just as I was going to the Ladies Chamber, I had a Letter brought me from the Count of <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slon,</hi> wherein he sent me word, that having well consulted, and reflected on all the reasons, that his Lady had urged to him, to oblige him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home, with those that I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on the same subject, he thought himself unable to deliberate alone on a matter of that importance, and that he was going to advise with some of eminent knowledge and Piety, that he might from them take his measures, as to what he ought to do, and that he would let me hear from him as speedily as he could. This Letter I carried to the Countess; who was over joyed to find that her Husband was not so very steadfast in his resolutions as she had apprehended. So soon as we had dined, I prayed her to keep her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; and having conducted her into my Closet, she, without further Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, thus began her discourse.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199411:13"/>
                  <head>THE HISTORY OF THE HERMIT</head>
                  <p>SInce the Relation that I am to give you, Madam, is really true, I suppose, you do not expect to find it so divertising, and stuffed with such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Adventures, as if it were a devised Tale. I shall not trouble you with a great many unnecessary things, neither do I promise to be so succinct, as I ought to be, for I am very sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, that I am often transported with pleasure, when I fall into the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of a Husband, who is so dear to me. I need not tell you his birth, since he hath discovered to you his Name; you know that his extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is illustrious, seeing he springs from a House, which hath given ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199411:14"/> Counts to <hi>Provence.</hi> He is not the eldest of the Family, he had two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and several Sisters; he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to be a Knight of <hi>Maltha,</hi> and having been admited at the same time with one of his Brothers seven or eight years older than he; the elder of these two Knights carried the name of <hi>Freslon,</hi> and the younger that of the Family, being of a very sweet and mild disposition, and fit for stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his Father changed the resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he had taken of sending him to be a Page to the great Master, and designed him for his Studies until he grew strong enough to be able to perform his <hi>Caravans.</hi> He was sent to <hi>Arles,</hi> and boarded in a Citizens house, there he applied himself to all that he was set about with such suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess as surpassed the expectation of his Masters The Man with whom he boar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, had a Daughter much about the age of the <hi>Chevalier de Belges.</hi> She was pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enough, though her features were no way regular, but a fine skin, white teeth, and lovely hair, rendred her very agreeable: it may be said, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199411:14"/> her wit was greater than has ever been known of any of her Age. It had been good for her, that she had had less of that, and more of reserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and discretion. Never was Maid more adventurous, nor of quicker ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension. She learned Italian and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine by observing the Lessons that were given to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> with whom she was frequently in company. But whilst she was busied in learning strange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, Master <hi>Cupid</hi> gave himself the pains to teach her how to love. <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia</hi> (for so she was called) found the Boarder so fully to her mind, that she could not forbear to love him. For his part, tho he had no great inclination for her at first, yet he took delight in her company, and (if I may say so) fell at length insensibly in love with her. You know, Madam, that the passions of people of that age are not usually violent; and therefore I shall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with a particular Relation of all that passed between them, for the space of three or four years; I must only tell you, that as <hi>Felicia</hi> grew in age, her flame increased; and there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199411:15"/> happened at that time an adventure, which served much to augment it. You are not ignorant, that all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> over, people are much addicted to Horoscopes; which makes a great many give out, that they are skilful in a Science, wherein few have ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood any thing. There arrived at <hi>Arles</hi> a man of much reputation for the Mathematicks; and was especially reckoned a great Astrologer. Seeing he was not to stay long there, all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were eager to see him. Many young Students of Quality went to wait on him; and some dayes before he was to leave the place, he repayed the visits which he had received. The <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> was in a Garden with five or six of his Comrades, the day that the Astrologer came to visit him: and the Master of the house, who was in discourse with another man of age and learning, drew near to the young Gentlemen, that he might assist them in receiving he visit of that able Mathematician. His conversation was at first about very indifferent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but seeing men of learning turn
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199411:15"/> alwayes their discourse to high, and sublime things, after several others they fell at length to talk of Astrology. The old-man, who was with <hi>Felicia</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and who tampered a little with the Stars, obstinately maintained the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility of that Science. But the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who was far more skilful than he, said, that there needed so many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances to ground a solid judgment on matters, which could not be known but by conjecture, that he was perswaded no body should apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to it. He spake afterwards in so modest and reserved terms, that it was easie to be perceived, that he had no great desire to make known his skill, though the Company begg'd it of him, and put to him several questions. Sometime after the Company depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, came a Woman to inquire for the <hi>Chevalier. Felicia,</hi> who alwayes care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully observed all that concerned her Lover, endeavoured to discover what the Woman had to say to him: but her curiosity was changed into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, when she found, that they discoursed in private: she had a mind
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199411:16"/> to ask an account of the matter, and her quick and mistrustful imagination made her spend some very bad hours, tho in reality she had no ground for it: For that Woman, who lived with her in whose house the Stranger lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, came to tell the Chevalier in his name, that if he was very curious to know any thing of his Fortunes, he offered him that satisfaction, on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition it might be done with secresie, so that he might not be importuned with a great many, whom he had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, nor a mind to satisfie. The Chevalier joyfully accepted the offer, and agreed, that next morning he should come down into a Summer-house of a Garden of the same house; which had a door, that opened into a little Lane. The Chevalier took the key, <hi>Felicia</hi> perceived it, and that so increased her jealousies, that she spent the whole night at the Window, that she might see when the Chevalier went out. No sooner began the day to break, but she perceived him in the Court undrest. Down she came; and having followed him at a distance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199411:16"/> and without noise, she hid her self near the Window of the Summer-house, amongst some bushes of jesamin, and so placed her self that she might see without being seen. Her joy and surprise was very great, when she per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that instead of what she sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, all these intrigues were only managed for obtaining an opportunity to speak with the old Astrologer: she resolved to pursue her curiosity to a point, and having drawn a little nearer, because she could not hear where she was, she over heard these words. If the Goods of Fortune can render you happy, you may have ground to be satisfied, seeing you are certainly to enjoy a large share of them: but if that blind Goddess be favourable to you, <hi>Cupid</hi> in revenge will work you much mischiefe, or to say better, you will occasion to your self a great deal, by giving way to violent extremities. There is indeed such a confusion in that matter, that I cannot unriddle it; all that I can know of certainty, is that you shall marry one whose for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune shall wholly depend on you.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199411:17"/> You shall meet with great crosses both before and after you marriage, and your greatest misfortune shall come from a woman with whom you shall be in love; and she likewise most passionately with you, besides I find that you are to have for some time a misunderstanding with her who shall be dearest to you: but she at length will give you proofes of so tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and shall undertake so much on your account, that you shall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain reconciled in a time when it shall be least expected by both, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est puzle I meet with, is to perceive that you shall fall into a fearful jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie, and to find that at the same time, she who shall resign her self to you, shall never admit of my Rival in your love. I see no cross in all your life that shall be caused to you by men; yet I cannot forbear to tell you, that I have never met with any thing more obscure and confused than what I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve in your fortune: for you have a signature that might make one judge assuredly, that you are to be of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious order, and nevertheless it is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199411:17"/> certain you shall be married, I can tell you no more; and I doubt not, but you will think all that I have told you extravagant. I am not surprized at it, for, I confess, I understand it not my self, and I find so great contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions in the accidents of your life, that I lose my self when I dive into them. Having said so he held his peace, and left the two persons before whom he had spoken very little satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his art, having not so much as found one word of sense in all his discourse. He for whom it was made thanked him very civily for the pains he had taken, and excused the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity of his words by the uncertainty of future events, it being the will of God that we should not be able to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into his secrets, nor to know his methods with us in this World.</p>
                  <p>I doubt not, Madam, but you will think, that I have spent much time in relating to you a very trivial matter; but it will not seem so to you, when you have understood the sequel of this discourse. I must tell you then that <hi>Felicia</hi> being in an alley, which but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199411:18"/> on the Arbour of Orange trees, heard all that was told her lover. She presently applied all to her self, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that she was the person whose fortune he was to make by marriage. Nor did she doubt but that the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that design would meet with a great many crosses; but that seemed no difficulty to her: for it was her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour not to love a good fortune, if it did not cost her cares, trouble, and intrigues. At night, when she saw the <hi>Chevalier</hi> again, she hinted to him that she knew somewhat of that which had been told him in the Garden. I know not, said she to him, if I ought to congratulate with you for the blessings which fortune promises you, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the crosses which you are to meet with in those very affairs wherein, in my opinion, the heart is extreamly sensible: but however it be do me but in the least justice, and you shall have no cause to doubt of my sentiments in every thing that concerns you. I give so little Faith to all that is called Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scope, answered the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and besides there is so little reason in that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199411:18"/> which has been told me to day, that I have not in the least minded it. But, continued he with an air that spake more gallantry than passion, if any thing can make me give faith to what has been told me, it is that I find already in my heart that violent flame which is to set me on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of so many things; and I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose you already guess at all the pains that I shall thereby suffer hereafter. Some that came into the Chamber where <hi>Felicia</hi> was, interrupted this conversation; and that did not a little vex her: for she impatiently longed to make the <hi>Chevalier</hi> explain himself, as to the share which she hoped to have in his fortune. Shortly after this, Madam, there befell the <hi>Chevalier</hi> a very considerable misfortune; I mean the death of my Lady his Mother. She was a Lady of great worth, and cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed her Children with all imaginable care and affection. The young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was sensibly affected with his loss, and it was not long before he felt the greatness of it by a sad experience. For his Father, by too common a piece
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199411:19"/> of injustice cast his eyes and care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his eldest Son onely; and even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that he wronged him, if he divided his kindness amongst his other Children. As he was a man, who was altogether taken up with his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, so he never meddled with his domestick affairs, his Lady had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes discharged that care. His Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren therefore found experimentally the loss they had sustained; for by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees their Father omitted to send them what was necessary, at first he neglected only the expences that were allowed for their curiosities and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures: but by piece and piece began to forget to send supplies to their neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities. The Chevalier <hi>Belges,</hi> who who was of a liberal and generous disposition, suffered that proceedure with very great impatience; and fell thereby into a fit of melancholly, that wholly altered his humour. <hi>Felicia</hi> was one of the first, that took notice of it, whether it was by the frequent Conversation they had together, or by the concern, that she took to her self in the matter. On this occasion she
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199411:19"/> fell into the thoughts, which are but too common to the most part of those who would vie in love. I mean, to desire that our Friends might meet with some Cross, provided it may furnish us with opportunities to render them conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable services. <hi>Felicia</hi> having gone to the Chevalier, tenderly upbraided him for concealing the cause of his vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Chevalier excused himself with some silly reasons, and at length told <hi>Felicia,</hi> that it would be a bad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the obliging inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, which she had in him, to burden her with a troublesome confidence. I should have hoped, said <hi>Felicia,</hi> that I might not have stood in need of so much sagacity, and that you would not have made a Mystery of a thing, which I desire not to conjecture, but that I may remedy it to your own sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: I should have been more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to you, if you had been free with me, than if you had bestowed upon me a Crown; but seeing the matter is otherwise, I shall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with greater reproaches, only I desire, that you would accept of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199411:20"/> what I offer, if you would calm this bad humour into which the little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence you have shewed me on this occasion, hath put me. With these words <hi>Felicia</hi> presented the <hi>Chevalier</hi> with a purse lined with a considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sum of money, he was very loath to accept of it, and it cost her many intreaties before she could perswade him to accept of a little, whereof she knew his need was indispensable. I know not, said she, what reason you have to be so ceremonious with me: But if it be true, as your words, and above all my heart perswades me, that I am one day to be so sensibly oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, deprive me not of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of shewing you some small ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement in advance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all that I have hitherto done, and all that for the future I can do, is to procure my self a happiness, which I desire more than my life: you doubt not, I suppose, added she, of the tender affection, that I bear you; but possibly you have been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ignorant, that I am the most ambitious Maid in the World; for to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199411:20"/> be short, your Quality alone without your Merit, was enough to dispose me to favour you, and your Merit alone without your Quality could inspire into me a tender affection; judge then what inclinations I ought to have for one in whom I find all that my heart can desire.</p>
                  <p>The Chevalier made answer in terms expressing more of wit and civility than passion. But they, who are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love, have not alwayes such discerning eyes as to perceive, whether they be beloved or not; and tho that be the most important concern of life, yet we are pleased to be beguiled by those whom we love; and our Reason is alwayes the Fop of our Heart, tho we would perswade our selves, that it is the Mistress. When the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier was alone by himself, he reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed seriously on all the proceedings of <hi>Felicia.</hi> The hope that she had testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to him of being one day his Wife, lessened in his mind much of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of what she did for him. He thought not himself obliged to have so great an esteem for that which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199411:21"/> from a principle of interest, as for that which springs from a source of Generosity and affection. From that time he indeavoured dextrously to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate to the Maid, that the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he had for her, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lead him so far as she believed. He had not so much time as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, to succeed in that design; for some few dayes after that conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereof I have been speaking, he had news that his elder brother was killed in the Army, and that his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was so sensibly touched with the loss, that his life was in danger. This advice obliged him to make ready to go see him. <hi>Felicia</hi> used all her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to divert him from a journy, which put her in extream affliction: But notwithstanding of all her discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, she felt some secret joy, when she considered that the predictions made to the <hi>Chevalier</hi> began to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. You are not ignorant, Madam, that in such conjunctures as the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> was in at that time, there is need of mony for a great many things. <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia</hi> offered him some with the same
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199411:21"/> earnestness as at first. He accepted so little of it, that she well perceived so finall a sum could not do his business: she went therefore to a Banker, who had a correspondance at <hi>Maltha;</hi> and having delivered him four hundred <hi>Pistols,</hi> prayed him to go to the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier de Belges,</hi> and tell him that he had received orders from the <hi>Chevalier de Freslon</hi> his Brother, who was at <hi>Maltha,</hi> to pay him in that money: The Banker punctually performed what he was desired to do; but the <hi>Chevalier</hi> being much surprized to receive such as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance from his Brother, not only because he had received no Letters from him, but also because he believed him short of mony as well as himself; presently told the Banker that he was mistaken; but the man having assured him of the contrary, told him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all his scruples, that he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence from <hi>Maltha,</hi> that four Knights of <hi>Provence,</hi> had taken a great prize at Sea, and that in all appearance his Brother was one of them. At length he suffered himself to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to do a thing wherein a great
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199411:22"/> many would have made no difficulty. <hi>Felicia,</hi> before his departure, omitted nothing to increase a passion on which she grounded the happiness of her life. She used all her skill to draw from the <hi>Chevalier</hi> some positive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise which might oblige him; but he dextrously avoided all occasions of long conversation with her. His ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty and civility made him loath to deceive a Maid that loved him. I shall not trouble you with a relation of the farewells that passed between <hi>Felicia</hi> and her pretended Lover. They were civil and discreet on the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s part, but full of Transports and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion on the Lady's: a thousand times she assured him that her love should last as long as her life, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would be too hard for her to preserve the right which she thought she had to his heart. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> promised never to forget the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he had to her, that he would give her Testimonies of a constant and perpetual gratitude, and that he would ever love her. He spake to her even more passionatly than he had ever done
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199411:22"/> before; for he was of a tender and sweet disposition; and left a young Lady with whom he had conversed for the space of four years, for whom he had entertained a kindness, and in whom he had inspired a passionate love.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> upon his coming home, found his Father in a great affliction as he had imagined; and though the death of his elder Brother might have given him hopes that his Father would have greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect for him, and that his kindness, not being limited to one single object, would spread it self on all the Family; yet all these reflexions wrought no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect on the <hi>Chevaliers</hi> heart, he lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the loss of his Brother, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed as much grief as his Father, like one that had really a good nature, and tender disposition. After he came home, he was at first taken up in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving all the consolatory visits that were rendered to his Father; but so soon as he had disingaged himself from matters of that Nature, which are in use, the very troublesome to those
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199411:23"/> who are in sorrow: The first spare time he had, he imployed in visiting his eldest Sister, who was married a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout twelve or fifteen leagues off in the Principality of <hi>Orange</hi> towards <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vignon.</hi> I cannot tell if I gave you an account in the beginning of the State of the Family of the Count of <hi>Freslon.</hi> I think, I told you but barely, that he had three Sons, and several Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the eldest of which was married to the Marquess of <hi>Rochevile,</hi> considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both for Quality and Fortune. He died some years ago, and left his Lady a Widow with six or seven Children. I was one of that number, Madam; and that you may understand the rest of the discourse, I must tell you, that the Marquess of <hi>Rochevile,</hi> my Father, who, as I have already hinted to you, had his Lands near to <hi>Avignon,</hi> went frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that pleasant City, where he saw a young Lady of Quality, who was put into a Monastry by her Parents, that she might be a Nun. He fell in love with her, and after many adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which I shall not trouble you with, he married her in spight of all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199411:23"/> his kindred, who, considering only the advantages of fortune, disliked a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage wherein there was no inequality but that to be found. The Ladyes parents thinking themselves affronted by the impediments that was objected to the marriage, believed their honour concerned not to consent to it, so that the business was done in spight of all. An affair attended with so many cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, could not be compleatly happy; and if I may so say, my Fathers hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness lasted but a moment; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a year after the marriage, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioness died in childbed of me. She recommended me to her Husband by all that was dear to him, and above all things prayed him never to force me to be a Nun. She had had sad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the rigour of parents upon that account, and told her husband that she would die in dispair, it she thought that she left me exposed to the troubles which she had suffered on that occasion; my Father promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all that she desired of him, and it may be said his promise was sincere, since time never bloted out of his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199411:24"/> mind the assurances that he gave her, and that he punctually executed all that she desired at her death. When time, which is the infallible cure of greatest sorrows, had mitigated my Fathers grief, his Parents obliged him to marry again, and cast their eyes on <hi>Mademoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon.</hi> They saw in her all that was to be desired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was for birth, beauty, or even for fortune. For though she was of a Family wherein were many children, yet her Grand-Father by the Mother, settled a considerable Portion on her before the marriage was concluded. My father acquainted <hi>Mademoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> that the most sensible mark of love that he could require of her, was to have a great kindness for me, and that amongst all the qualities that rendered her desirable, that which made him most earnestly court her for a Wife, was the sweetness of her disposition; because he thought, that since he must give me a Mother-in-law, he could not chuse any who would use me so kindly as she. He was not out in his conjecture; for so soon as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199411:24"/> the marriage was cellebrated, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from her all the markes of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that I could have desired of a Mother. My Father, after he had lived with her nine or ten years, died of a Feaver. He left to his Lady, whose Prudence and Virtue he sufficiently knew, the disposal of all his estate, and recommended nothing to her so much on his death-bed, as that she would continue her goodness to me. It was about two years after that great loss, that the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> came into that Country. His Sister had alwayes entertained greater kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for him than for the rest of her Brothers; and amongst other reasons that obliged her to that, the strongest seemed to be drawn from the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full resemblance that was between them. It was so great, that except the difference of cloaths and age, it was hard to distinguish them; my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law being near forty years of age, and the <hi>Chevalier</hi> not above twenty, after the death of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Freslon</hi> their Mother, one of the Sisters the youngest of the family,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199411:25"/> was sent to live with her Sister. She was a Lady of an ordinary beauty, and of a crafty and artificious temper, her Father could never oblige her to stay in a Monastery: for when she was placed into any, she played so many tricks to all the Nuns, that they were forced to beseech her Parents to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move her with dilligence. When her Sister received her into her house, she told her plainly, that she would have her to live quietly, and let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alone; and she promised to do what she was enjoyned. I am afraid, Madam, I have been tedious, by a long digression, which I was obliged to make to inform you of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of a Family, which by the sequel of the discourse you will find were absolutely necessary to be known. I shall return then to my subject, and tell you, that I never saw my Mother-in-law enjoy a moment's content since her Widow-hood, but at that time when she saw her Brother. He seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me very handsome, and, I think, you will easily believe it, since that in the sad condition wherein you have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199411:25"/> seen him, he retains still a good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough mien to shew that he must have been a most compleat person. At his first visit I received of him a thousand testimonies of civility, which I attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted only to the complaisance that he had for my Mother-in-law; and in that thought I was far more solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to pay him the honours of the house, than to all others that were wont to come thither. My Lady <hi>Rocheville</hi> perceived it, and told me one day in raillery, that she desired for my sake, that she might be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently visited by those for whom I might believe she had a Singular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, because she hoped it might make me lose somewhat of that wild hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which she so often reproached me with. Seeing it as been alwayes my thought, Madam, that none can discourse handsomely when they speak of themselves, I have hitherto shun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to tell you any thing of my person. But for two reasons I find my self now obliged not to be so peremptory in the resolution that I had taken as to that, the first is, that having no more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199411:26"/> the qualities for which I have been heretofore praised, I cannot now be Proud of them; and secondly, that the Beauty, which some pretend I then had, may excuse the violent passion that my Husband had for me. I must tell you then, Madam, that my beauty was naturally regular, I had a good voice, and played indifferently well on the Guitar; my temper inclined more to meloncholy than mirth: and all that were not throughly acquainted with me, imputed to vanity and pride, what was only the effect of a timerous and reserved disposition. I confess, notwithstanding that I am a little vain; I cordially love all that, I think, I ought to love, and never undervalue my self when the Interest of my friends is concerned. I was naturally so mild and timerous, that they, who had the charge of me, never found occasion to give me long rebukes; for I appear'd to them so much affected at the least thing they told me, that there was no need of great discourses to make me amend. You have, Madam, in a few words my character, when I first
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199411:26"/> saw the <hi>Chevalier.</hi> He stayed with us fifteen dayes at his first visit, and during all that time he let no occasion slip to let me know, that the complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance, which he had for his Sister, was not the only ground that obliged him to have the same for me. The sad condition I am in, Madam, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me from relating to you a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand particulers, which with pleasure I should recount to you at another time; I shall only tell you, that I thought the <hi>Chevalier</hi> had some incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for me; and I likewise perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that I was not indifferent at his departure, and that if he rendered me all the services that I desired, he would not find me insensible. He omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing that might please me when he took leave of his Sister. He told her he had received a Letter which obliged him to go to <hi>Avignon,</hi> and that he would use his endeavours that he might have time to see her inpassing upon his return. He kepthis word and come back four days after, he seemed more addicted to me then than at the first time, and though he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199411:27"/> had resolved to spend but one night at <hi>Rocheville,</hi> yet he stayed two dayes compleat: His Sisters attributed that stay to his good nature, and it was not his fault if I did not impute it to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother cause. He assured me at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if his Sister judged of his love by the care he should take to send and come himself to learn news of us, she should have all reason to be satisfied with him. I made him no answer to these words, for I was not willing to enter into a discourse which I understood but too well. Alas! Madam, Love is a great Master, I was young, had no experience; yet I well perceived that the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s words were sincere; and at the same time felt in my self some sentiments in his favour, which I had never had for man. I saw so little appearance that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement we might have together could come to any happy success, that I thought it would be imprudence to let such sentiments encrease in my heart as could not but create me trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I urged to my self on that head all that a most experienced person
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199411:27"/> might have alleadged to me, and thought by the resolutions which I took, that I had said enough to my self to stifle a passion which was not as yet fully grown. I began to think my self past all danger, when the <hi>Chevalier</hi> came back to <hi>Rocheville.</hi> I was a little vexed when I perceived in my self the alteration that the fight of him wrought in me. yet I put so much force on my self as to hinder it from being discovered, but I can not declare to you the surprize. I was in, when I found that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> spake much less to me than he was wont, and carried himself towards me in a way quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what he had formerly done. The sense that I had of that procedure, convinced me that my heart was not so free as I had believed. One evening as I was fetching a walk alone, <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> came to me, Sister, said she, for so we called one another, I have just now had the greatest pleasure imaginable in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing of you two hours compleat, with one who hath asked me a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand questions concerning you, for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199411:28"/> no other end but that he might have the pleasure to make me speak many things to your advantage: I prayed her to explain her meaning. She told me that her Brother had discours<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her all the morning of me, and had not omitted to question her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout all that concerned me, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly about my humour. I was a little surprized at that discouse, but was not ill pleased to find thereby that he concerned himself more in me than I believed. Seeing I put no great confidence in the person that spake to me, I told her that I thought there was not much seriousness in what she acquainted me with, and imputed only to curiosity the questions that had been put to her on my account. We were still upon that subject, when our conversation was interrupted by the visit of some Ladies of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-hood, to whom we were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to pay the civilities of the house: we conducted them in, and having left them in a roome, I pretended some business in my Chamber, that I might there muse with ease on all that had
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199411:28"/> been told me: but I had not much time for reflexion; for I was hardly got into my Chamber when the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> came in. He seemed to me more melancholick than he used to be; and as he entered he begg'd me pardon for interruping some business, which might undoubtedly be more agreable to me than the trouble of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, but protesting he could no longer resist a desire that he had to speak to me in private. Seeing you can have no business with me, said I to him smiling, which requires a long audience, I believe you may tell me all you have to say in the time that we are going to the rest of the company, saying so, I gave him my hand that we might goe out of my Chamber, and made appear by my countenance that I would not take it well, if he should be obstinate to remain there. He went instantly forth, and we went together straight to the place where we left all the company; but found them not there; for these Ladies were gone to walk in a grove of Orange trees. You see, <hi>Madam iselle,</hi> said the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199411:29"/>
                     <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that heaven favour my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, since it affords me an occasion of speaking to you in private; you will suffer me, I hope, to make use of it, and to beg of you two favours; the one is, that you would fully believe all that I shall say to you, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that you would answer me frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I shall find no difficulty, said I to grant the half of what you desire, since I never failed in sincerity to any body. But I cannot conceive continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I, looking seriously on him, what can be the intent of your discourse; but this I know, that you will much oblige me to reflect on the person to whom you speak. He assured me that he had rather die, than in the least de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate from the respect that he owed me, and that the sentiment which he had for me, though made up of affection yet contained nothing that might give distaste; and for a proof of that, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured me, that he durst never have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the love he had for me, if he had not had good ground to hope, that he might bring matters so about as that he needed not doubt of his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199411:29"/> happiness, if I would but consent to it. I know, Madam, added he, that I might imploy a thousand more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and passionate expressions to open my heart to you, but I am better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convinced, that the wittiest discourses are not alwayes the truest, and that the surest mark of love, that can be given to a Lady, is to desire to be joyned with her in such bonds as nothing can break. Tell me your mind, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you, and let me know if you have any repugnance to receive the offer which I make you. I will owe your heart to none but your self; and am sensible that I have done nothing as yet that may deserve it, but when I have learned from your fair mouth, that you have no aversion to me, there is nothing which I will not do to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain▪ somewhat more advantagious. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> said no more, and have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept silence for some time, that he might give me leisure to answer, and perceiving by my countenance, that I was very much puzled. Speak, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, said he, speak, but for lov's sake, do it with that sincerity you promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199411:30"/> I ask but two words of you; tell me if you find in your self a dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition one day to love me, or command me never to appear more in your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence; but once more speak: for I know no condition more cruel than to be in a state of uncertainty. I believe you are not surprised, said I to the <hi>Chevalier</hi> at the confusion into which your discourse has put me: The small experience I have in the world, and especially in such matters, makes me that I know not what to answer; but since I must keep my word to you, in speaking sincerely; I must tell you that my thoughts of you have nothing that looks like hatred, and that no vows of mine shall ever make you complain of your fortune: but have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declared this truth to you, you will take it in good part, that I repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to you my fortune not to be such as may promise any thing to my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. You know that I depend on my Lady your Sister, and that all the good and tranquillity of my life is at her disposal; in a word you are not ignorant of the condition of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199411:30"/> and you ought to be less ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant that I will do nothing without the consent of my friends; and that there is no likelihood they will approve a settlement, that will be so prejudicial to you. All these reasons have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged me to strive against the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I felt for you, and to pray you to overcome the passion which you profess to have for me, seeing it can never succeed to the advantage either of your self or me. You may possibly, added I, accuse me of too much credulity in answering so serious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to what you have proposed: but I have alwayes thought that most part of women, who turn such kind of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses into raillery, are not displeas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be plyed with them still; and for my part, I should be much afraid to hear the like often. I am so over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed at the first words you have said to me, answered the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and and my heart is so filled therewith, that melancholy can find no place there, and that I may let you see my fortune is not so bad as you take it to be; I'le tell you one thing, that none of this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199411:31"/> Country, but my self knows as yet, That is, that my brother the Knight of <hi>Maltha,</hi> who is advanced in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der either by time or the services that he hath performed, hath made his vows two or three months before he heard of the death of my elder Brother. He hath sent me word, that he is no more in a condition to forsake that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and that though it were free to him to do so, yet he would never change it for another. He hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated me to chuse the fittest time to acquaint my Father with that news: and I have resolved to tell him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it until I knew what fortune I might expect from you. I had no time to answer his last words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we were told that they stayed for us to come to Supper, during which; I observed that <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> endeavoured to read in the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of her Brother and me what kind of discourse we had had together in our evenings walk: when all the company had withdrawn. I went to my Mother-in-law's Chamber, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told by her Maids▪ that she was in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199411:31"/> her closet, I approached to the door, and having made a little noise that she might know that I was there, she bad me come in. Having shut the door after me, I know not, Madam, said I to her, what you will think of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course that I am to tell you, but I know very well I should be altogether unworthy of the kindness wherewith you have honoured me, and of the care you have taken of my education, if I concealed from you any thing that may concern me. I must tell you then Madam, that your Brother hath spoken to me in such a strain as gives me ground to believe he has some kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for me: but seeing my judgement is not ripe enough to discant on such matters: I hope you will take it well; Madam, that I refer my self to yours. Having said so, I told her word for word the whole conversation that her Brother and I had had together; and besought her so to order my conduct, that I might do nothing whereat one day she might be dissatisfied, she in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted me not during the whole time of my discourse; but when I had
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199411:32"/> made an end, embracing me with Motherly affection; I praise God, Daughter, said she, that all the care I have taken for you, has met with a disposition that hath surpassed all that I could have desired. You have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to believe that the interest of my Brother shall never banish from my heart your concerns; and seeing of all the advantages that are desired in marriage you want nothing but a fortune, and that by a thousand other qualities you supply the defect of that which is not essential to the happiness of life, I think my Brother too hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in having you for his Wife. You may trust to me as to a Mother, who most dearly loves you; you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly delighted me in speaking to me as you have done; I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perceived my Brothers inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards you, and some there have been who have endeavoured to do you bad offices with me. We had much discourse on this subject, and at length she advised me to trie as exactly as I could if her Brother spake to me with so much sincerity, as he endeavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199411:32"/> to perswade me. For to be short, continued she, we are of a sex that ought to guard against the dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, and we cannot be too cautions to secure our selves from that. When I had returned into my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and reflected on all that had been said to me, I made no doubt but that it was <hi>Mademoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> who had sought the occasion to possesse her Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster with prejudice against me. I had for a long time observed, that she bore me a spight, and that she had sought all wayes to do me an injury; but I seemed alwayes ignorant of it, as well because I delighted not in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, as for the respect I had for my Lady her Sister; and I endeavoured by all kind of solicitude and little of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, to overcome her unjust machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Now seeing the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was to depart next day; I was sensible that we could not renew our conversation, and the rather because I had resolved to give no occasion to the young Lady his Sister of entertaining any new sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions of our intelligence. I made it my business all the day to pay the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199411:33"/> civilities of the house to these Ladies who came to visit us; and seeing I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted alwayes in musick, I prayed the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to give me the lines that were made at <hi>Avignon,</hi> to an air which he had taught me. As he was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that, he dropt a paper out of his pocket; his Sister took it up, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perceived by him, and made me a sign that we should go read it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: I told the <hi>Chevalier</hi> that I could not refrain from the curiosity I had of seeing somewhat that his Sister intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to shew me, but promised to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it to him, if it was worth his pains. I had not done so, if I had not thought that that Lady, who was naturally destrustful had suspected that I was concerned in that Letter; so I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thdrew with her into a window that we might read it; and in it we found these words.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>VVHere it as easie▪ for me to break th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> bonds that detain you where you are, as it was to tear the Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change which I send you back, you should have no pretext that might hinder you from</hi>
                                 <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199411:33"/>
                                 <hi>seeing me again. I am not satisfied with your heart, I find nothing of it in all your Letters; they are civil, but they are short, and of a cold and perplexed stile: and that which gives me a total alarm, is your great exactness in paying of a debt which no body craves you for. Think rather of acquitting you self of one for which I am afraid you will become bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, for I am so punctual to my duty in all that I have promised you, that you cannot perform yours, if you be not des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly in love with me. You know me, and on that account I will not take bad mony for good coyn: I require heart for heart. You are engaged to it; and nothing can excuse you from keeping your word. I send you some Letters from</hi> Maltha <hi>which are addressed to this place for you. The engagement wherein your Brother is, hath made me reflect much on your horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scope. Alas! what would I not give to see all these predictions fulfilled. Farewel, I perceive I am like to say more than I would, and perhaps also more than you desire. When I began to write this Letter, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to quarrel with you for the mony you have sent me, but I want strength to</hi>
                                 <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199411:34"/>
                                 <hi>do it, I am still the same, or to say better I am a thousand times worse; seeing time and absence, which serve to cure other evils, do only encrease mine: Adieu, send me long Letters, but never any more Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>I shall not tell you my thoughts, Madam, whil'st this Letter was a read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; never was heart in so violent an agitation, and I had so little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of my self, that his Sister might easily have discovered all that she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to know, had she but observed me. I did all I could to reassure my self; and told the Lady, that if I had thought that that Letter had been so dear to her Brother, I should have had a special care not to have vexed him by reading it. I only spake these few words, and took some simple pretext to retire a little in private, that I might recover my self from the trouble that so unexpected an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had put me in, so soon as I found my self so composed as to appear, I returned to the company. I found them all busied in playing upon the <hi>Chevalier</hi> for the Letter that his Sister had
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199411:34"/> read. He justified himself like a man who seemed not much displeased at the discourse; but I engaged as little as I could in all that foolery. So soon as the <hi>Chevalier</hi> could come to speak to me in private; good now, Madam, said he condemn me not without a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unless you intend to force me to despair. It will be hard for you to excuse you self in my mind, said I, and I never pardon a Gentleman who is cruel, or even indifferent towards a Lady, and I so compassionate her that writes to you, that though I know her not, yet I take her part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, and I could almost do any thing for her satisfaction. I spake these words in such a manner as might give him to understand that I was not well satisfied with what I had seen. Once More, Madam, said he, I adjure you to give me a minutes hearing; and what prejudice soever you may have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived against me, I hope, you will be so just as to acknowledge me innocent. Deny me not then the favour that I begg, unless you intend to force me to make use of the authority that my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199411:35"/> Sister has over you, that I may obtain a short attention. I was so curious to hear the particulars of an adventure, which put me already into so great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, that it was no hard matter for the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to obtain his desires; especially seeing I had all the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that I could wish for, to speak to him, because the rest of the company were fallen to play. He began his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with fresh assurances of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection he had for me. He gave me an exact relation of all that happened to him at <hi>Arles;</hi> and there appeared so much frankness in the assurances he gave me, that he had never entertained more for <hi>Felicia</hi> but a kindness of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that I could not but be satisfied. He made me also take notice that she complained of him in the Letter that was in question. In a word, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, the reasons of one whom we love, easily perswade and gain credit, and that conversation which with so much peevishness I had begun, ended with reciprocal assurances of an inviolable love: but I considered not, Madam, said the Countess to me; that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199411:35"/> of a happy time, so pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesses my mind, that I am not aware that this relation is too long, and may prove tedious to you. I told her that I should be ravished to spend the whole day in hearing adventures wherein I sensibly concerned my self. Having given her that assurance she continued in this manner the rest of the evening. It was impossible for me to entertain a long discourse with the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> he told me only that he would be gone next day without taking leave. He assured me that for ever he would prove constant in his love, and make all the haste he could to return.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the first Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199411:36"/>
               <head>THE Penitent Hermit. OR <hi>The Fruits of Jealousie.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
               <p>IT is needless for me, Madam, to tell you the trouble that the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> caused in me; because by telling you that I loved him sincerely, and that my heart is naturally very soft and tender; I think, I have given you to understand in a few words, that I am not insensible when any thing comes to me from the beloved object. The time in which the <hi>Chevalier</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to return was not as yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, when he came to <hi>Rocheville:</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199411:36"/> and that exactness of doing more than he had promised filled me with joy; but I was exceedingly surprized to observe a great deal of melancholly and anxiety in his countenance; which encreased the impatience that I had of speaking to him in private. He being no less impatient than I, made us quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find an occasion of entertainment. He informed me, that his Father upon his return told him that he designed to marry him to a Maid of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinay fortune; that he had done what he could to divert him from that resolution: But that seeing he was a man steadfast in his purposes, he fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to exasperate him, and that he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told him with all imaginable sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and mildness, that besides the natural aversion that he had to marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, he had no likeing to the Maid that was proposed to him, who was fearfully ugly: He told me that he was come to find some consolation in my Company, and to consult with me on the means to prevent so unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a disaster. Though I did not expect that a matter of that importance could
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199411:37"/> be concluded so very suddenly, yet I found my self much afflicted at the news, and that which increased my trouble, was a firm resolution that I had taken, never to enter into a family, without the consent and desire of those that were chiefly concerned in it. The example of my Mother obliged me to take that resolution, which I declared to the <hi>Chevalier;</hi> and though he would have willingly desired other marks of my kindness, yet I still persisted in that mind, and he continued unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able on his part in the resolution he had taken not to listen to any propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition concerning that marriage. He told me, that he had some hopes that when his Father should understand that his Eldest Son had made his vows and was professed, he would allow him some more liberty: But that he was unwilling to discover any such thing to him, least that by so doing he might have created himself some new trouble. He likewise told me that at his departure he had not told his Father whither he was going, and that it was thought he was gone to pay
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199411:37"/> some Visits elsewhere, and that he could not tarry with us above a day. We spent that whole day in bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our cross fortune, and in contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wayes to render it more happy. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> discovered himself to the Marchioness of <hi>Rocheville</hi> his Sister. She answered him like a good and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Lady, and thought it enough to tell him that she could give no advice in a matter that might displease the Count their Father; but that she could neither oppose his designe, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to her the more reasonable, that she was confident he could never f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a wife with whom he could spend his life with so much content and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as with me. We resolved all three together to wait till Heaven might be pleased to dispose more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably the mind of the Count of <hi>Freslon,</hi> and that in the mean time we should use all circumspection to hinder him from discovering our love. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> departed next morningly by times, and from that day I began to feel by sad experience the pains of those who are sincerely but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199411:38"/> unfortunately in Love. On a day when my thoughts were taken up in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sad reflexions on the success that the business which lay nearest my heart, might have, I was told that my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law called for me; I went to her Closet, and was exceedingly sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to see her eyes bathed in tears. It is not, said she, shewing me a Letter, to purchase your thanks for a displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure that I have just now received, that I have sent for you; but only that I may divide with you all the troubles that we are like to meet with. When she had said so, she read a loud a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the Count her Father had written to her, wherein he reproached her, for countenancing the foolish pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion that his Son had for me; he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerated the discontent that that wrought in him, and the rage which it put him in against my Lady his Daughter, in so rough terms, that I was not at all surprized at her afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I cannot express how much I was moved for having been the cause of her trouble. I was so sensible there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that the very thought of it sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199411:38"/> in my heart all the reflexions that I might have made upon my own calamities; I shall not trouble you with a relation of all that we said on this occasion. We concluded, that it must needs have been <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> who had acquainted her Father with the love that her Brother had for me, and that which the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed us in that belief, was, that she had testified to my Lady her Sister, that she was very desirous her Brother might marry the Lady that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to him, because she hoped there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that she might have some share of her great portion, which might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure her a speedy marriage. I earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreated my Lady, her Sister, that she would speak nothing to her of our suspicion, and at the same time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought her to suffer me to go to <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnon</hi> there to abide for some time with one of my Aunts: I was the rather indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to beg that of her, because I hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it might justifie her to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as to the accusations he charged her with on my account, and besides I had a secret design in that journey,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199411:39"/> which was to put my self into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastery, and there to continue all my life time, rather than to expose the only persons whom I loved in the World to crosses and misfortunes for my sake. I had special care not to discover my designes; because I was very sure that she to whom I spake, would never have consented to it. I had even much ado to perswade her to let me take that journey, and I may truly say that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was greater love between a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Daughter-in-law, than was between us. At length I departed on the journey I have been telling you of, and I wanted not pretexts for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, because all my Mothers kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred lived in that City, or in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood; yet never was journy made with greater affliction: so soon as I was at liberty, I gave my self wholly up to sorrow; which was the greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I had laid violent constraints on my self to conceal it before my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I have been so loath, Madam, to tell you things unnecessary, that I have forbore to mention many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars which might have been necessary
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199411:39"/> to the sequel of my discourse, I must tell you then that the love I had for my Mother-in-law, having hindered me to go to my Mothers relations, what entreaties so ever they had made to me after my Fathers death, exceedingly vexed them; and especially one of my Unkles, who had alwayes profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a great kindness for me. I made the pretext of my journey to be a visit to his Lady, whom I had never seen since her marriage; and I had no great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to make my peace with my Unkle. When I came to his house, he was just upon going to <hi>Avignon</hi> with his Lady, there to spend the Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val. If my inclination had been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, they would not have made that journey; for a country retirement was far more proper for my melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick humour than the noise of the City, where all was mirth and jollity, and especially at that time. Whil'st we were at <hi>Avignon</hi> I meet with an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected accident, which put me in great confusion; for my Kinswoman, who was young, and minded only to spend her time with pleasure, took me with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199411:40"/> her, one evening that she was invited to supper, to a great house where a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort of musick was provided; where after we had danced some time, the Marquess her husband was let in. I was very glad that the tumult had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me from constraint: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pretending to be weary, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be in a place where I might be taken out to dance, I retired into a corner of the Hall. I had not been long there, when I espied one in the habit of an Egyptian, who, having looked every where about, came and fell on his knees before me. I was not at all surprized at that carriage; for, you know, Madam, that <hi>Provence,</hi> is the place of the World where Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers are the gallantest: but I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to perceive that the person, who had been so solicitous to draw near to me, looked on me a long time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out speaking a word; which made me laugh a little. I asked my mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer if there was no body in all the Company to whom he could talk plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singly; he answered me in Italian with a counterfeit voice, that men were
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199411:40"/> often silent because they had too many things to say, and that he durst not trouble my meditations. I told him, that I took his answer as a good excuse for his silence, and assured him that he had pitched upon the right person when he came to me, if he had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to speak; since I took alwayes pleasure in silence. I am surprized, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered the Mummer; that such a Lady as you can be melancholick; I thought sadness ought to be the portion of wretches, such as I. You will confess that no man can be more, when I have told you the perplexity that I am in. You know that we are of a profession that allowes us nothing but what we steal: I cast my eyes on one of the fairest young sheep that ever was; I believed my self sure to catch it, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless it has escaped at the time when I least expected; and that which is most grievous to me, is that I serve a master, who will never let me rest, untill I have found again what my ill luck hath made me lose. I took this discourse for an invention to play the part of an Egyptian, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199411:41"/> himself, that he had been so slow in speaking to me; I resolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Act, and told the Mummer, that I pitied his accident, but that I hoped he might find somewhat on his way, that might comfort him for his loss. Your hopes may pass for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies, Madam, answered he, for since I have been with you, I find my mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune much lessened; and if you will grant me the least assistance, I hope I may see my troubles at an end. The Egyptian spake these last words in a way that much perplexed me. If you would have me render you any good Office, said I to him, you must deserve it by a piece of complaisance, which I desire of you; it is easie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, since all I desire is that you would tell me your name; I confess to you I am very desirous to know it, and the name of that Master, who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges you to so painful a search. I shall willingly tell you my Masters name, said the Egyptian, drawing a little nearer me; the small acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance you have with him makes me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid you will not concern your self
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:199411:41"/> any more in his affaires, when once you have heard it. You must know then that <hi>Love</hi> is my Master, and were I somewhat less unhappy than I am, your heart would have already explained to you the whole riddle, and you would have known the person that speaks to you. I needed no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clearing, and at these words I knew it was the <hi>Chevalier de Belges,</hi> who spake to me under the disguise of an Egyptian. I know not whether my joy or surprize was greatest. I prayed him, that was the cause of it, to tell me what good Genius had brought him so quickly to the place where I was. He told me, that having gone to see my Lady his Sister, and having missed me there, he had inquired where I was; and that having stayed a day at <hi>Rochevile,</hi> he had departed from thence without communicating to any where he designed to go, and that having none with him, but a <hi>Valet de Chamber</hi> in whom he could trust, he had taken Post to come to me. That being the same evening come to <hi>Avignon,</hi> he had learnt at the Inn where
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199411:42"/> he alighted, that there was a great Ball that evening, where all the Ladies in the Town were to be; and that he resolved to come thither in disguise that he might endeavour to speak with me; and to take from me his measures how he should behave himself towards me in publick. Having testified to him my acknowledgement for the trouble he had put himself to for my sake, I told him, that I thought it not fit he should stay long at <hi>Avignon;</hi> that I was affraid, if he did, it might cut out more work for him with the Count his Father. He seemed unwilling to follow my counsels on that occasion; and seeing the pleasure of seeing one whom we love, carries commonally greater sway than the fear of discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which are but seen at a distance, I gave consent that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> might spend the rest of the carnaval at <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnon.</hi> I thought that the divertis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which at that time are to be found in that City, might prove a rare pretext to warrant his abode there; our conversation lasted very long, and I was as loath to leave that assembly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199411:42"/> as I was to come into it. The <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> thanked me for all my pains in so passionate a manner, that I thought all that I had done for him nothing in respect of what he deserved.</p>
               <p>So soon as I returned to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I went in all haste to bed, that I might muse with my self at greater ease. The night was almost spent when I began to fall a sleep, and that was the cause that it was late before I awoke. I was not as yet out of bed, when my Unkle entered my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and rattled me for my laziness. You have reason, said he, to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of your beauty, for it produces very extraordinary effects: you will believe it when I have acquainted you with the visit I received this morning. With these words, having desired the Maids, that were in my Chamber, to withdraw, he told me that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess of <hi>Doursan,</hi> who was a man of great age, and no less fortune and merit, had been with him that morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to tell him that he had so great an inclination for me, that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to essay by all meanes to oblige
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199411:43"/> me to admit his suit, but seeing he perceived that the language of Love did not agree with gray hairs, he found himself obliged to implore his assistance to obtain my consent in the design he had for me; and that he so referred all his concerns to him, that he declared he would grant me all the advantages that our family could desire. This is the thing, Neece, said he, that I have to impart to you; you know your fortune is not suted to your birth, it is therefore my opinion you should not reject the propositions I have made to you. That discourse put me into a terrible vexation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I well foresaw that that matter would hatch new impediments to the engagement I had with the <hi>Chevalier:</hi> I answered my Unkle with all possible civility; but so chose my words, that I gave him no positive reply. Seeing it was already very late, he left me that I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght have time to make my self ready; but my mind was so taken up with what I had heard, that I did not much heed my dress, and I longed much to see the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that I might
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199411:43"/> speak with him. Whil'st my thoughts were so employed, one of his Servants entered my Chamber, and asked me in his Masters name, if I thought fit that he should pay me a visit after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and if I would have the goodness to present him to those with whom I was. You may believe I made no great difficulty on that occasion to grant his desire. Immediatly after dinner the <hi>Chevalier</hi> entered the room where we were; and so soon as I had told the Company who he was, they received him with much civility. We had spent already some time in general discourses, when a <hi>Valet de Chamber</hi> having whispered my Unkle in the ear, he went out of the room, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again immediatly. Ladies, said he, looking at me with a smile, I am employed to pray you to take the pains to go hear a consort of Musick in one of the pleasantest houses about <hi>Avignon:</hi> I am charged to perform the civilities of this entertainment, and that it may be the more agreeable; I have liberty to chuse such as I please to make the Company. I knew very
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199411:44"/> well by the air my Unkle spake with; that the regale came from him whom he had spoken to me of in the morning. Had I been, absolutely my own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress, I would have stayed at home: but it was in vain for me to think of that. The <hi>Chevalier de Belges,</hi> being all the while present, he was intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make one of the company, and it was no hard matter to perswade him, because of the pleasure he took to be with me; and seeing he, to whose house we were going, was his near Kinsman, my Unkle charged him to acquaint five or six jolly Women, and some Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our gang. Whil'st my Unkle was busied in giving his orders, the <hi>Chevailier</hi> drew near to me; I cannot, tell, said he, if I be mistaken: but I think you are a great deal more melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than ordinary, tell me what ground you have for it. I cannot satisfie your curiosity said I to him, unless we were in another place; and I assure you that the greatest regale that I propose to my self in the place, whither we are going, is, that I may there find some oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aking to you with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199411:44"/> I had hardly spoken these words, when they that were to go with us to this ceremony, entered the Room, and immediatly after we all took Coach to go to the place where we were expected. It is certainly one of the loveliest places in the world, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for situation, or the pains that have been bestowed upon it. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not, Madam, that I will give you an exact account of all the rarities that are to be seen there, nor of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures and divertisments that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded us. It is tedious to me to read long descriptions, and I find so few that pleasantly make them, that I shall have special care not to engage in such an undertaking. I shall only tell you, that what ever abundance, neatness, gallantry, and magnificence could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise, was to be found in that entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that my old Lover took an opportunity to tell me his mind whil'st the Company was taken up with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an admirable consort of Musick. I observed that notwithstending all his gravity he could not forbear two or three time to change colour as he drew
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199411:45"/> near me. I know not Lady, said he to me, leaning on the back of my chair, if your Unkle hath spoken to you of the discourse we had together this morning, but I know very well that your merit must far exceed all that I have hitherto seen, seeing you have inspired sentiments into me which I never knew before; it is misbecoming a man of my age to confess his folle, but when one wants strength to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, he ought to betake himself to the goodness of his Conquerour. I am not so blind as to hope that you entertain a reciprocal passion for me; but if you have not an insuperable aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to my person, I shall endeavour by fortune to repair the defects of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Pardon me, I pray you, Sir, said I, if I answer not seriously to a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course which I look upon as an exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of your wit to divert your self by trifling from the great affaires wherein you are imployed. This I said, with so much co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>sion, that the good man believed it was only bashfulness that made me so unwilling to hear him; so that having spoken two or three words
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199411:45"/> more on the same subject, and the consort being ended, he changed his place. We were desired to go into a large and fair hall, and the <hi>Chevalier</hi> catched an opportunity to give me his hand. What I see here, said he, when he was near me, begins to displease me, and I am much mistaken, if all the Philosophy of the Master of this house can defend him against your charmes. Before he had said this we were got so near the rest of the Company that I could make him no answer but by a nod. After supper, we were pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly surprized to see the preparatives of a Comedy, which was presently acted. In a word, Madam, we found so many occasions of divertisement in that place, that it was day before we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Avignon.</hi> Seeing I had not slept for two nights together I found my self so weary as to have need of rest and to lye pretty long a bed. I was next morning much surprized, to see the Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi> enter my Chamber; who, after some discourse about the divertisements of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeing night: I should esteem my
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199411:46"/> self happy, Madam, said he, if such things might oblige you to approve the design which I have for you. I am sensible that I speak not to you with all the Gallantry that might be expected from a young man: but I am so old, that if I would undertake to attack your heart in the usual formes, I should be dead before I made half the journey. I confess, Madam, I found that way of courtship so pleasant, that I had a great mind to laugh; yet I was a little uncertain how to answer that discourse, and the rather that my new Lover would needs press me to assure him that I disliked not his person. I make no doubt, said he, but that your Relations will consent to my happiness, I have a considerable estate, and in this age, that is all that is minded: But, Madam, I will not purchase you as a slave, nor will I buy your heart, I will endeavour to merit it. If he that spake to me had been of another age, I should have been less puzled to answer him, according to my real sentiments, but his age and merit
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199411:46"/> imprinted some respect on my mind. Whil'st I was considering how to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer him, the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> eased me of the trouble, by coming into my Chamber. I blushed at sight of him, as if I had committed a crime in hearing love from any but him. The Marquess attentively observed me, and shortly after went out. So soon as I was at liberty I told the <hi>Chevalier</hi> all that I had met with concerning that proposition of marriage; who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed terribly afflicted thereat. You may easily believe, Madam, said he, that it is not jealousie that causes my griefe: but I only fear that your old gallant's estate may object strong impediments to my hopes; and to confess my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, I fear, I shall never be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence what you sacrifice for me on this occasion. You have sacrificed so many other things for me, said I, that it is very just I should testifie my gratitude to you, and that I have never loved you for interest. We spent the rest of that conversation in contriving wayes to divert the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune thath both of us apprehended.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:199411:47"/> So soon as the Marquess's design was blazed abroad in the City, his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons omitted nothing that might prevent that mischief: but all their pains were fruitless, and the Marquess persisted steadfast in his resolution, the oftener I saw him, the greater I found his merit and civility to be, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, had I not been unalterably engaged to the <hi>Chevalier</hi> I would have preferred that Illustrious old man to all others. I think it is pertinent Madam, in this place to give you an accout who this Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi> was, you shall know then that his birth and fortune were very considerable, he had lived long a Widower; and having had a Son of great worth, had placed all his affection on him; but he having been killed five or six years before, he appeared so sensibly affected for that loss that he seemed to have renounced the World. His course of life since that time perswaded two Neeces of his, whereof the one was Married to an <hi>Italian,</hi> and the other to a man of little merit, to reckon their Unkles estate their own. It may be easily
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:199411:47"/> then imagined what discontent these persons had to see themselves in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of losing so considerable a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. One day, when we were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in my Aunt's Chamber, where all the rest of the Company was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged at play, wherein I went shares with the <hi>Chevalier de Belges;</hi> I could not forbear now and then to ask him about the fortune of our play, though I seemed attentive enough to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the Marquess of <hi>Doursan.</hi> The Marquess observing it, tell me the truth, Madam, said he, having earnestly beheld me; the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to whom you speak is not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to you. I confess it, said I, a little surprized at his discourse, and I shall never be indifferent to any thing that concerns the Marchioness of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheville;</hi> you know he is her Brother. I am not ignorant of that, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he, I know not as yet what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution I should take: I love you as much as I esteem you, and that puts me to a plunge. The Marquess having said so left me; and I was so troubled at what he said, that if he had stayed
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:199411:48"/> longer with me, I would freely have confessed to him the state of my heart. Seeing it was late when they left play, I could not satisfie the desires I had of speaking to the <hi>Chevalier;</hi> I only pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, as he went out, to return as soon as he had supped. We were gone from Table a long time before I heard any news of the <hi>Chevalier;</hi> and I knew not what to think of his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligance; but seeing it was not his custome to be so, for such things as I desired of him, I was afraid that some accident might have befallen him. Whil'st my mind was distracted with these thoughts, there came in one of the Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi>'s Lackeyes in great disorder, who told us that his Master had almost been murthered, and that he had certainly been killed had he not been rescued by the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier de Belges.</hi> You may believe that this relation put us in great astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My Unkle went immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inform himself of the particulars of that accident, and to satisfie the intreaty of his friend, who desired to see him at his house. I asked the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:199411:48"/> Lacky if his Master was wounded, and if the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was with him, and in what condition he was; he told me that his Master had received a very considerable wound, and the <hi>Chevalier</hi> another in the Arm, which he did not think was dangerous; but that seeing he was not present, when the matter happened, he knew not all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. If it had been decent for me to have waited one my Unkle to the place, it would have eased me of much anxiety. About an hour after he returned, and told us that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess, after he left us, having gone to visit one of his friends, who lodged hard by his house, had sent back all his attendants and kept only one La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckey with him; that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing by that door, because it was his way to the place where he was to sup, had heard three men talking together. I fear, said one of them, that by use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much circumspection we shall lose our promised reward. I know not, answered his Comrade, if I be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, but I think this the best occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on that we have as yet found, to cure
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:199411:49"/> the good man for ever of his itch of marrying. Take right measures, said the third, for I do what I can, I come to give you notice where he is, and I am going to him, for fear that if he miss me, he may take some others to wait upon him home; which would spoil our whole design. The last having said so went back into the house. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> pondered a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with himself, if he should set upon the Rogues; but being uncertain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom their design was, he chose rather to stand near the door where he saw the boy enter; and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Lackey, who carried his light to retire into a street at a little dist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and to be ready to come to him at the first noise he should hear. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had he given these orders, when he saw the Marquess come out attended only by one Lackey; he had made but two or three steps into the street; when these two men that hid themselves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a gate, advanced with drawn swords and were followed by two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; they were just about to have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Marquess when the <hi>Chevalier</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:199411:49"/> cried out, and calling his Lackey, threw himself betwixt that Illustrious old man and him that set upon him. Yet he could not so defend himself, but that he received a cut in the Arm. Another of the Murtherers came pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently in and engaged the Marquess, having given him a wound on the shoulder; but the <hi>Chevalier</hi> made him repent his boldness; for having sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated him a little from the rest, he put him out of condition of ever commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such crimes again. His Comrades, being terrified by what they saw, made it their business to escape the like fate. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> wounded another of them as he was making up to the Marquess; which put them into so great terrour, that they betook themselves to their heels; so that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> had no more to do, but to go home with him whom he had so vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly defended. My Unkle told us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, that he never saw a man so grateful as his friend was, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour which he had received. I care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inquired of the condition of their health; and understood that their
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:199411:50"/> wounds were but slight, that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess's was somewhat greater than the <hi>Chevaliers</hi> hurt; and that he would by no means suffer his Defender to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of his house. When the first trouble, that that news had wrought in me, was a little over, I was overjoyed that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered service to one, who of all men living best deserved it. I sent next morning to know how the wounded did; and learnt that the Surgeons as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured them that their wounds were not dangerous, and that in eight or ten dayes they might come abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. My Unkle desired me to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany his Lady in a visit which she payed these two generous friends: and there being a great many in their Chamber, they could only speak to me by their eyes. My heart being in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destood very well the language of his looks. He told me, as I was going out of his Chamber, that he hoped his hurt would not long deprive him of the honour of waiting on me. Next day after, I understood that the Count
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:199411:50"/> of <hi>Freslon</hi> was come to <hi>Avignon</hi> upon the occasion of the accident that had befallen his Kinsman and Son, which, as all things are magnified by report, was made appear to him to be far greater than really it was. I was very apprehensive that the coming of the Count into a place where he might see me, or at least could not but hear much talking of me, might not revive in his heart the discontents that on my account he had conceived▪ against his Son, the thought of that obliged me to write to the <hi>Chevalier de Belges,</hi> and pray him to keep his Chamber longer than he intended, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the services, which he could not forbear to render me, would exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate the mind of his Father. I lay at that time under such agitations as may be better imagined than expressed, when I was informed that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess of <hi>Doursan</hi> had sent to intreat my Aunt to come and spend the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon at his house. His Age, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposition, and quality, and above all the custome of the Country, made the matter very feisable; and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:199411:51"/> tell whether the fear of finding the Count of <hi>Freslon,</hi> or the pleasure of seeing his Son, wrought the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est effects on my heart, but seeing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure is a passion more agreeable than fear, I gave way to that which most flattered my heart, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take courage against the rest. When we entered the Marquess's Chamber, we found five or six of the most considerable persons of the City of both Sexes. The first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliments, and some indifferent dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, being over, one of these Ladies, who rendered the civilities of the house, proposed to go to play. This divertisement pleasing all the Company, they were easily engaged. They had the discretion to remove a little from the Marquess's bed, least the noise might incommode him. There remained none near him but a Lady of quality and my self; and she being called upon about business was obliged to go forth. So soon as the Marquess found me with him alone. I thank Heaven, Madam, said he, for the occasion it presents me of speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:199411:51"/> to you in private; I have long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired it; yet this pleasure, how great so ever, cannot be perfect unless you promise to answer sincerely to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions I am to propose to you; if that be all, said I smiling, that is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to render this conversation agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, I assure you you shall have all cause of content; and though my hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour were less free than it is, yet it would be impossible for me to dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with one whom I so much esteem as I do you. Having that assurance, replyed the Marquess, I shall not stick to ask you if I was mistaken, when I thought that you were not insensible to the passion that the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> has for you; for, I fancy, that in your eyes I have read the secret of your heart; but, Madam, continued he, dare I be so bold as to confess my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, what I have told you has troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me, but not changed my resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of endeavouring to enjoy you. I love you even to adoration, and yet that passion is not so great as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem that I have for you. I cannot think of yielding to another, unless
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:199411:52"/> I know that my pretensions displease you. In a word I need your help a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your self, that I may obtain a Victory for which of my self I am too weak: assist me then for pity's sake to us both; if it be so that you cannot love me, tell me the reasons that may oblige me to love you less. At these words he stopped expecting my answer; and though I found my self at a loss, yet, I saw, there was a necessity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring my self; yea and I had some hopes of moving him to compassion; so that striving against my natural bashfulness I answered him in these terms. When you thought that I was not insensible to the passion that your Kinsman hath for me, I confess, you have hit on the true sentiments of my soul; but I must tell you with the same candor, that if all my relations did agree to order me to Marry you I would obey, though I be fully sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, that that obedience would cost me the repose of my whole life. Think not, added I, that any aversion to you would have rendered my submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion so grievous, but it is my heart
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:199411:52"/> that can love none but the <hi>Chevalier de Belges;</hi> it hath resigned it self to him without my consent; and when my reason examined the conduct of my heart it hath found so great worth in the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that it hath approved the choice; so that nothing can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve an engagement which inclination and reason hath warranted. Good now, Madam, said he, tell me if you well foresee all the consequences of an affair which seem so dangerous to you. The long experience that my years have furnished me with, assures me that merit alone compleats not the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of this life; and that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Riches, which many brag of, is a kind of Philosophy easie in the theory, but very difficult when it is put in practice by pinching ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity. Consider then what you are about to do: I am rich and old; the one promises you a considerable settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the other a short captivity. Cannot I move you to pity your self and me. It surprizes me, said I to the Marquess, that you can have any esteem for me; and believe me capable
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:199411:53"/> to bend my thoughts to such low and base things; and since you will not understand what I have already told you concerning the real sentiments of my heart; I must again tell you, that there is nothing but what I would do to hinder me from being yours; but if I be constrained to it by reasons of honour and duty, which I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist, I shall not be guilty of the least word or desire that may displease you, or contradict the virtue whereof I make profession; and though that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence should cost me my life, I should more contentedly lose it, than be guilty of any thing wherewith I might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached. What you have represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me as to my interest and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, might have wrought upon me, were I not to involve the <hi>Chevalier</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a share of my pains; and the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship I have for him is so disinterested, that I would do any thing to please him, though at the expence of that which might be dearest to me. With these words I stopped expecting his answer. I thank you, Madam, said the Marquess, for your sincerity; and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:199411:53"/> though I was prepared to hear a part of what you have told me, yet I must confess it hath deeply affected me. Having said so he held his peace and fell again a musing; shortly after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing his discourse; but what cause have I to complain, said he; have you not assured me that you will obey your friends, and can I desire more of you? I was surprized at these last words, and imployed all the eloquence that heaven had bestowed on me, to perswade the Marquess of <hi>Doursan,</hi> that a Gentleman could never be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, when he enjoyed his Mistress by forceing her inclination. I was still engaged in this discourse, when the Company left off playing, and drew near the bed where we were; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was late, it was thought fit to withdraw, and as the Company went away they made a short stop in the Chamber of the <hi>Chevalier de Belges:</hi> where I had not the occasion to speak so much as one word to him without witnesses. Next day we were told that the Marquess had relapsed into his Fever. That accident was by all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:199411:54"/> attributed to the noise that had been made in his Chamber; but I knew o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more probable and apparent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons for it. One evening having shut my self up in my Chamber, that I might mournfully reflect on the unhappy state of my fortune, my Unkle came in and told me that pressing reasons obliged him to intreat me to go with him to my Lady of <hi>Rocheville</hi>'s house, and that it highly concerned me to hasten thither with all imaginable secrecy. I was surprized at such an extraordinary proposal, and earnestly desired him to tell me the reason of so sudden a journey. He promised to satisfie me by the way; and seeing I alwayes pleased my self with the hopes of seeing my Lady of <hi>Rocheville</hi> again, and that the hurry and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities that I met with at <hi>Avignon</hi> made my abode there uneasie, I seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inclinable to undertake that jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: so that having spent two or three hours in ordering some little affairs that I had to do, and in taking leave of my Relations, I was ready and took Coach. The night was
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:199411:54"/> calm and fair, and we made as great progress in our journey, as if it had been day. I was very desirous to have acquainted the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> with my departure; but seeing it was dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to find at such an hour those whom I used to trust in delivering him my Letters, I was satisfied to forbear until I came to the place whither I was going, which might furnish me with a great many occasions to let him speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear from me. I endeavoured on the rode to satisfie the curiosity which so strange an adventure excited in me; but my Unkle turned all my questions into raillery; and I came to <hi>Rocheville</hi> without discovering any thing of what I desired to know upon that subject. The Marchioness of <hi>Rocheville</hi> received me with the sincerest testimonies of affection; and so soon as I was at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty I gave her an exact account of all that had befallen me, since I left her; who with her accustomed good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness told me that my interest in every thing was her own.</p>
               <p>I had not been there above five or six dayes, when on an evening, as I
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:199411:55"/> was fetching a walk I saw a Coach come to the gate, which I knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Count of <hi>Freslon.</hi> That sight put me into a commotion which I could not resist when ever the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> of <hi>Belges</hi> was concerned; but my trouble encreased when I saw the Count of <hi>Freslon,</hi> after that he had sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted my Lady his Daughter, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards me, as a man that had somewhat to say to me; yet instead of a cold and indifferent address which I expected from him, he applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to me with a kind and chearful countenance. I know not, said he, presenting me a Letter, if the good news, I am told you will find in that paper, may oblige you to have some goodness for him that has undertaken to deliver it; but I am confident if you be such, as I have been told you are, I have ground to hope for some share in your friendship. I never found my self so tossed as I was at that time; and I may say, that joy, hope, and fear made such a confused medley in my mind, that having so many things to think on, I could think on
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:199411:55"/> nothing; and to compleat my pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, whil'st the Count of <hi>Freslon</hi> was in discourse with me, the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> entered the Chamber where we were; who having been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes diverted, when he came out of the Coach, had not instantly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Father. I cannot tell what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer I made to the discourse of the Count; but in all appearance my words spoke most the disorder of my mind. The Count of <hi>Freslon</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out minding that much, prayed me to read the Letter which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to me, wherein I found these, or words much to this purpose.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>
                              <hi>IN fine, Madam; I have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and if the greatness of the Victory be to be reckoned by the sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the conflict, this that I have gained upon my self, is of inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable value; but that I may not prove a false Bravo, I confess to you, that I could never have triumphed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the assista<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ce you gave me. It</hi>
                              <pb n="108" facs="tcp:199411:56"/>
                              <hi>is just then that I divide with you the price of the Victory. I reserve to my self no more than the pleasure of procuring your happiness, and the hopes that you will cherish my memory. This is all that I desire; and you shall judge, Madam, if my ambition be great, when you shall learn what I have done to procure you the only blessing whereof you have assured me you were sensible. I am still too much captivated to your charmes, to hazard an interview so soon. When time and reason have confirmed my heart in the resolutions that I have taken, I shall come and rejoyce with you, that I have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased the happiness of your life by the full repose of my own.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>After the reading of that Letter, I continued wholly suspended betwixt compassion and the desire of being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleared of what I could hardly guess at, and durst not declare my curiosity;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:199411:56"/> but my Lady of <hi>Rocheville,</hi> who was almost as curious as my self, besought her Father to tell us what we earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desired to know: which he did in this manner. Three or four dayes after I came to <hi>Avignon,</hi> the Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi> sent to intreat me to come to his Chamber; he discovered to me all the particulars of his Love for <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Rocheville;</hi> and having described to me her merit and person, in such a manner as was necessary to excuse the violence of his passion, he told me he was resolved to give her the most extraordinary mark of his love that could be given; but that he could not have that satisfaction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my concurrence. Though I could not imagine what service I was able to render him in that affair, yet I free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promised him, to do all that I could in his behalf. Having given him this promise, he told me that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to settle the half of his estate on the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> in testimony of the obligation he had to him for having so generously exposed his life for the preservation of his, and that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:199411:57"/> he would give him the other half, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition that he married <hi>Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiselle</hi> of <hi>Rocheville.</hi> Having said so he told me the obligations which my Son stood engaged in to that lovely Lady; but that which hath affected me most sensibly is the candid and disinterested way of procedure that she hath alwayes used towards these two Lovers. You may believe that the offers of the Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi> were every way too advantagious, not to be accepted with pleasure; and the rather seeing his nearest relations hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing basely forfeited all title to his goodness, nothing could hinder me from embraceing the kindness which he desired to shew to my Family. We had nevertheless about the end of our conference a pretty odd debate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by my unwillingness to accept the whole estate wherewith that generous Kinsman had a mind to gratifie our Family. Having at length prevailed upon my unwillingness, and all things being ordered as we judged most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, he prayed me not to delay the satisfaction of two persons who
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:199411:57"/> were dearest to him; and even desir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the matter should be kept so secret, that the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> himself should be ignorant of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations he hath to him, untill that nick of time wherein he might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand their value. This is the true account of what the Count of <hi>Freslon</hi> told us. Had I not observed the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of joy which the <hi>Chevalier de Belges</hi> expressed during that discourse, I should have believed that nothing could have equalled mine. But, Madam, it is no purpose to persist longer on this point. The Count of <hi>Freslon</hi> kept the word that he gave to his generous Kinsman of cellebrating our marriage with all the expedition he could. My Unkle, who brought me to <hi>Rocheville,</hi> was there still, and had learnt from the Marquess of <hi>Doursan</hi> himself all that the Count had told us; but being obliged to secrecy, he would not till then discover it. In fine, Madam, that marriage so little expected, and so earnestly desired, was at last concluded. The Count of <hi>Freslon</hi> on that occasion omitted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:199411:58"/> that might clear my mind of the discontents that I might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived against him. My Lady <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> seemed fully as sensible, as her Brother or I, of the happiness that we were to enjoy; there was none but <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon,</hi> who, according to her natural inclination, grieved at the felicity of others. For my part, I did not affect such a garb of unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable modesty, as to appear less sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible than indeed I was; and I thought it impertinent to conceal an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which was in a few dayes to be warranted by an engagement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though love be wanting yet it must be pretended. In a word, Madam, our marriage was solemnized; and though I needed no more but his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who was designed for my Husband, to render that ceremony agreeable, and that his thoughts were the same with mine, yet nothing was wanting in pomp and magnificence to encrease the pleasure of our Nuptials. At that time as in all other occasions of my life, the Marchioness of <hi>Rocheville</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted intreating me as if I had been
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:199411:58"/> her own Daughter. What shall I say, Madam, for the space of two years after my marriage, I thought that they, who say there is no perfect hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness in this life, were strangely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken; for by experience I felt, that there was nothing I could desire but the continuation of the blessings which then I enjoyed. I had a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band who loved me almost to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; I had no less passion for him: my Father-in-law by all imaginable tenderness repaired the troubles he had caused me. My Brother-in-law, who would not leave <hi>Maltha,</hi> testified by Letter that he was abundantly satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with our marriage; and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat my happiness, I so ordered mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that my Lady <hi>Rocheville</hi> and I were inseparable. But at length, Madam, Fortune persued me with her usual inconstancy; I mean, that having favoured me with great bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings; she frowned upon me by the greatest evils that I could apprehend; or to speak more Christianly, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was pleased to let me see, that none should set their heart on the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:199411:59"/> of this life; and that seeing our heart is created for him, he severely punishes the rape, when addicting it too much to the Creature, we forget him who is the Creator. I have not told you, Madam, that the first year of my marriage, I was brought to bed of my Eldest Daughter, whom you see hear, the year following I had a boy, and was very ill all the time I was with Child, but received of my Lady <hi>Rocheville</hi> during my sickness such services and cares as cannot be imagined. When I began to recover, there happened a business that oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to return home; and seeing she did not expect to stay but a few dayes, she left with me <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon,</hi> and my Sister, who was a lovely young Lady, about thirteen or fourteen years old, and whom I had alwayes tenderly loved. The day we expected her back, we were inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that she was fallen dangerously sick. I was smitten to the heart at the news, and immediately resolved, though I was near my time, and not well recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from my sickness, to go see that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:199411:59"/> dear Lady, that I might in some measure repay the services which I had received from her; but my Husband would by no means consent to the journey, and gave me so many reasons, which were indeed so just, that I durst not oppose them. He departed the same evening to go see his Sister, but his journey was almost useless; for she died four hours after his arrival, she had only time to pray him to have a care of her children, and to tell me from her, that she desired of me the same kindness for them, that she had had for me. You easily believe, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, what grief it is to lose a Sister, who is so tenderly beloved; yet though my Husbands affliction was inexpressible; after the first trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of it were over, he resolved to conceal the sad news from me, for fear that the grief, which he knew it would work in me, might not bring me to a relapse. He stayed as short time as he could in a place where he saw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but mournful objects; and seeing he had many things to order, he thought fit to charge his Sister with all
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:199411:60"/> that care. She had wit and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence enough in houshold affairs to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that office well. My two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were at the Colledge, and three of my young Sisters in a Monastery; in so much that my eldest Sister, stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with me, none of the Children were in the house when my Husband returned. He told me that the sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of my Lady his Sister was not dangerous; but that the Physitians believed it would prove long, and that she prayed me to send her Sister back to her, and to keep her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with me untill she her self came for her. Though I perceived very well that my husband was more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick than he used to be, yet he told me these things in so candid a way, that I doubted not in the least of the truth: I did even believe that my Lady his Sister was willing to remove <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> from me, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing she had observed but little friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship between us before her departure. My husband acquainted her with the loss we had sustained, and the reasons why he would have her go that jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:199411:60"/> Two months after the death of the Poor Lady <hi>Rocheville,</hi> I had so well recovered my health, as made it believed that that news could do me no considerable prejudice; it was discovered to me; and I was so sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly affected therewith, that I had ground to think that grief alone is not able to deprive us of life. Though at that time my Husband had busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which obliged him to make a pretty long journey, yet he would not leave me in the sad condition wherein I was. <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed four or five months after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and brought my Brothers with her, who had been taken out of the Colledge for some formalities of justice to which their presence was necessary. Their comeing renewed my affliction; but in a word, Madam, love is always more prevalent than friendship; I must needs yield to the intreaties that the Count made to me, that I would resume my accustomed humour. Amongst those that came from <hi>Rocheville,</hi> my Brothers brought with them a <hi>Valet de Chamber,</hi> who
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:199411:61"/> played rarely well on the Lute; and seeing I was alwayes a great Lover of Musick, and that that instrument of all others sutes best with melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick people, I delighted to hear him play. The affaires which I told you obliged my Husband to make that journey, grew so urgent that he could not delay them. When he took his leave of me, he many times adjured me to spare nothing that might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert me from melancholly. Besides he earnestly recommended the care of me to his Sister, who of late had begun to shew me a great deal of kindness. During the absence of my Husband, (seeing the little diversion that is to be found in the Countrey, makes people willingly apply themselves to the smallest recreations) I took an humour to learn to speak <hi>Italian.</hi> I had already a smattering knowledge of that tongue, but it was no more than to understand it; and you have, possibly, found by experience, that when people love sincerely, they do nothing but what has some reference to the person belvoed, so I fancied to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:199411:61"/> my self a pleasure in writing <hi>Italian</hi> Letters to my Husband; because that tongue without doubt expresses bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than any other language the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der sentiments of a heart. My eldest Brother was sometime my Master in that study, but his own skill being but small, he told me that his <hi>Valet de Chamber</hi> could teach me far better than himself, seeing he was an <hi>Italian;</hi> and I had observed by his accent, when I heard him speak that he was a stranger. The young man gave me a lesson every day after dinner, and I found by his discourse, that he was more witty than such persons use commonly to be. On a day when I asked him where he had learnt to play so well on the Lute, he, weeping, answered me, that he was not born for the employment which he discharged, that he was a Gentleman, and of a family conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for estate: that he was bred with great care, but that his Father hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen into an unlucky accident, they were banished from their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, so that he was forced to betake himself to service, and that finding
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:199411:62"/> his humour a little too stiff to serve an imperious Master, he chose rather to wait on my Brothers, whose age and mildness gave him ground to expect less trouble than he could have any where else. I asked him his name, and the place where he was born. He prayed me to excuse him from giving me that satisfaction, because the hopes he had of recovering his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer condition, made him unwilling that any body should know what he had been obliged to do. That dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of <hi>Valantin,</hi> for so he was named, moved me to compassion. He begg'd of me not to discover to any body, what he had told me, assuring me it was of great consequence to him, that it should be kept secret. I promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him what he desired; but after that day, gave orders to the other Servants of the house, to treat him with some respect; and I had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more also for him my self, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause besides what he had discovered to me, I daily perceived that the Lad had wit, and dextrously performed every thing wherein he was imployed;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:199411:62"/> and I was the rather perswaded of the truth of what he told me, because he was free from all vices, to which such young men are commonly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. For that reason I was very glad to have him stay with my Brothers. Some dayes before they were to be sent back again to the Academy, <hi>Valantin</hi> fell sick, so that he could not go with them. About that time my Husband returned from his journy; and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then I had no need of other diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, when I was with him, I minded no more playing on the Lute nor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Italian;</hi> but I continued to have a care of <hi>Valantin,</hi> who was still sick. At that time there happened an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which hath occasioned me much trouble. A Gentleman of quality of our neighbourhood at my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, proposed to a Kinsman of his in <hi>Languedock,</hi> a marriage with <hi>Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiselle Freslon;</hi> and on that occasion matters were carried on in the usual way that is observed in most part of marriages; that is to say, all things were ordered before the parties had seen one another: but by ill luck, when
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:199411:63"/> the pretended Gallant came to make his first visit, he found <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> so disagreable, and my Sister on the other hand so lovely, that he took a strong resolution to forsake the one and make love to the other. He that concerned himself in the affair, in vain represented to him that his carriage was altogether unworthy and injurious, and that assuredly we would never give consent to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe he had for my Sister, having misbehaved himself towards a person so nearly related to us: but that was not the only occasion wherein we have experience that Love submits not to the Government of reason. I shall not give you the trouble to hear all the particulars of that adventure: I must only tell you that the <hi>Cavalier</hi> had but the half of what he desired, that is, that the marriage with her whom he loved not was broken, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused the other for whom his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was great. Seeing nothing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends our Sex so much as a slight, you may believe <hi>Madamoiselle de Fresson</hi> was not a little concerned at that affront.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:199411:63"/> Her hatred to me encreased; and though I had shewed such civility to her, as was no less than injustice in respect of my Sister, since I hindered her from a considerable match; yet she could not away with any of these reasons, and thought her self obliged to be revenged on me because my Sister was beautiful. The love I bear my Husband makes me loath to come to this part of my discourse, wherein I must of necessity give you ground to blame his conduct; but, In fine, it is his will that I should acquaint you with that part of his life, as I have done with all the rest. I must tell you then, Madam, that sometime after the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, I have spoken of, was broken off, I observed the Count to be very melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick. Since I had alwayes found his temper even and regular, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the alteration might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from some indisposition; I care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inquired into the cause of that molancholick for which I found no ground. He told me it was an effect of his constitution, whereat I should not be troubled. As I could perceive
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:199411:64"/> no more apparent cause for it, so I took that excuse for currant coyn. I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that perhaps the great confluence of people that were at our house dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased him; so that when company came, I found alwayes some pretext to retire into my Chamber, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my self about some trifle. The Count several times asked me why I did so; and seeing I durst not tell him the truth of my suspicions, I alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many times silly reasons to colour what I did. One day, when I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in my Chamher, my Sister told me, that she had a thing to acquaint me with, and that she was afraid I would not like it. I told her she would alwayes please me, if she discovered to me any thing that troubled her. The matter that I am to tell you, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded shed, concerns one who is nearly related to you, and I should not have spoken, had I not been apprehensive that it may do you some mischief. I bid my Sister quickly declare what she had to say. She told me that <hi>Valantin</hi> had great familiarity with my Sister<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-law; that she had several times
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:199411:64"/> found her two hours after midnight siting on his bed, and that there was hardly any day, but that they had some conference together; but that they were as secret as possible they could, and that she durst not seem to take notice of their commerce. I told my Sister that she ought not to judge so rashly of her Aunt, and that she should have a special care never to speak to any body of that suspition. When I had reflected upon what my Sister told me, I found the matter but too probable; and that made me resolve to send <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantin</hi> immediately back to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but being afraid to exasperate <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> against me, I was willing to ask her opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the departure of the young man. She seemed to be much against it; which put me, into a greater plunge. She told me, that she was to go to <hi>Rocheville,</hi> and that he must not be sent away before her return, because there were reasons of consequence that it should be so. My Husband was not present, when we had this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; he had quite changed his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:199411:65"/> humour; and whereas in the first years of our marriage we were inseparable: at that time he shunned my Company as much as he could. Never did any lie under such anxiety, as I suffered; the more I examined my self, the less could I perceive from whence my misfortune proceeded; and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat my misery, I began to think that some new amour might banish me from the heart, where I believed my self so well settled. That thought made me so sorrowful and peevish at the same time that I received all things snappishly. Seeing my jealousie had no precise object, I was the more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted; and resolved to gain some of my Husbands Servants. One night when we were in bed together, and that I upbraided him a little with his carriage towards me, to which he made little or no answer, he asked me of a sudden if I did not think of sending <hi>Valantin</hi> to his Masters. I thought the asked me that question only to break off the discourse that we were upon; and that having put me quite out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, I told him that I was much
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:199411:65"/> troubled at the perplexity my Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions put him into; that I did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the expence of single man should have so disturbed him; but that I should take order for that. The Count made no answer to these words; but turned himself to the other side in a huff. We spent the rest of the night both of us without sleep; and it was scarcely day when he took his Gown to rise. For all the discontents that I had against him, yet I repented that I had spoken to him so briskly, so that I made some attempt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade him to lye still; but he told me that he had a meeting about a busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of consequence, and that he thought he could hardly be back be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two or three dayes; having said so he called a <hi>Valet de Chamber</hi> to dress him. I peeped through the Curtains that I might observe him whil'st he stayed in my Chamber; I saw him walk up and down, like a man in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream disorder, and afterward draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near my bed. Farewel, Madam, said he, may Heaven restore to us that repose whereof we both stand in need.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:199411:66"/> With these words he left my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and went into his dressing room. I lay still in so great perplexity, that I knew not what course to take; I had several times a mind to have gone and thrown my self at my Husbands feet: but taking my self to be injured, and that my conscience upbraided me with nothing relating to him, unless it were of too great love; I knew not what to do; I called my Maids that I might rise, and at the same time heard a noise of horses in the Court; starting up, to see what the matter was, I saw the Count taking horse attended only by own <hi>Valet de Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> I had at first a mind to have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to him, but seeing that he took but one Servant with him, I thought he would return by night: I spent the whole day in extraordinary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation. Pretty late in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Sister came and told me, that <hi>Valantin</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gg'd of me that he might speak with me in private unperceived of any. I thought he might have some matter of importance to acquaint me with in relation to <hi>Madamoiselle</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:199411:66"/> of <hi>Freslon,</hi> and therefore I sent him word, that he might come into my Chamber when she had retired: and I was very willing to have informed the Count of what <hi>Valantin</hi> told me concerning his Sister; but seeing he was not like to return that night, I imagined that the Lad might have discovered something of my Husbands pretended gallantry, and that he intended to impart it to me. When all the house had retired, <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantin</hi> came into my Chamber: I was sitting in a Chair by the fire, and had sent out my Maids, telling them that I expected the Count that night, and that how late soever it might be, I would not go to bed till I heard some news of him. So soon as the Lad came into my presence, he cast him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self down at my knees, and begg'd me Pardon for the effects of an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant passion: you will be surprized, Madam, said he, when you know that at your feet lyes prostrate a Maid, whose name and adventures are not unknown to you. I am <hi>Felicia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Madam, and that name alone may
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:199411:67"/> make you guess at some part of my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; I believed the Count your Husband to have been in love with me, and I sincerely loved him; the grief that I conceived when he slighted me, had almost laid me in my grave. I was sick a whole year, and was glad that I thereby lost that little beauty which nature had bestowed on me, because having no return of love from him that I loved, I cared no more for being lovely. In fine, Madam, I had still a little beam of hope ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a horoscope, and that it might succeed, I changed my name and habit, and having gone to <hi>Rocheville,</hi> where I understood the Count was, I found not him, but <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> his Sister: next day after I came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I heard a conference which she had with a woman, wherein she seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give marks of a mortal hatred against you, and that she sought oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of doing you prejudice. The knowledge of that made me discover my self to her; and she assured me that she would do all that lay in her power to revive in her Brother his former
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:199411:67"/> flame; though that seemed no easie matter so long as he entertained the same sentiments for you that he had at that time: that she knew his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; that nothing but jealousie could work any great effect upon his mind: but it puzled her exceedingly that your conduct gave him no cause of conceiving any. What shall I say more, Madam, I have been made use of to inspire that passion into the Count; and it has in some manner suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: but when his Sister perceived that he broke not forth in violence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough against you, she proposed to me to poyson you. I looked upon that crime with horrour, and the indifference that the Count has for me hath cured <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantin</hi> of the evils that <hi>Felicia</hi> suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I have endeavoured to behold the Count with the same eyes that heretofore I thought so powerful on his heart; I got his Sister to speak twice to him of <hi>Felicia</hi> at my first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hither: he answered her that he had given you his promise never to listen to any discourse concerning that Maid, and that he had no mind to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:199411:68"/> break his word: his indifference for me hath cured me of a passion that for above these eight years hath ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over me. I promised <hi>Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon</hi> to do to you all that she desired, for fear she might apply her self to some other more wicked than my self. Take now your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures a tos the information I give you, and Pardon me for all the troubles that I have caused you; having said so, she delivered me a packet of the Counts Letters; with a Bracelet of his hair, and told me she would be gone next morning, and put her self into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastery. She begg'd of me mony to buy a womans apparel, telling me, that after the crosses she had met with, she would never again return to her own Countrey. As she ended her discourse she bowed down and kissed my hand. I protest, Madam, I was so troubled and moved at what I had heard, that I could not forbear to shed tears. <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> told me so many other things, that I made no doubt of the truth of her words. I took out of my pocket all the mony. I had, and gave it to that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:199411:68"/> poor maid, telling her, that if she need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more I would go fetch it out of my closet; but she kissing my hand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted what I gave her, and as she a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rose to be gone, I embraced her, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her all that I thought proper to comfort her in the sad condition wherein she was. She presently went out of my Chamber. But, good God, Madam, how can I express my sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, when I saw the poor Maid hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a great cry fall to the ground run through with a sword; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone to the door, I perceived my Husband hastily running down stairs. The violence of my grief had almost put me in the same condition, that <hi>Felicia</hi> was in, and I fainted away. The noise that that accident made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened my Maids, who were asleep in another Chamber, the Chaplain was called for and came in time to give the absolution to that poor Maid, who lived almost two dayes after. I saw nothing of what I tell you; for I lay above four hours in a swoon. When I was come to my self again, the first thing I did was to ask tydings of my
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:199411:69"/> Husband. I was informed that the Count passing through a hall that joyned to my Chamber met <hi>Felicia,</hi> as they were carrying her away; and that having beheld that spectacle with horrour, he returned that he might go out. For pity sake, said that poor Maid to him with a stronger voice than could be expected from her, deny me not the last suit that I am to make to you, it is no more but that you would with patience hear me speak one word; and I assure you, that I shall be so far from bewailing my own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that as <hi>Valantin</hi> I pardon you, but, as <hi>Felicia,</hi> give you thanks that by a favourable thrust you have put an end to the troubles which I suffered for your sake; my present state admits not of a longer discourse, and I ought to spend my last minutes in taking care for my Soul; but I am forced to tell you, that I am afraid Heaven will punish you for the unjust suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions you have conceived against the most Virtuous Lady that ever was: Farewell, added she with a dying tone; I die with content if the loss of my
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:199411:69"/> life may reestablish the repose of yours. Having said so, she made asign that they should carry her away. The Count, who began to hear that discourse by a bare inclination of natural compassion, fell into bitter regrets in the progress thereof; he discovered the truth of her words either by the features of her face, which he more narrowly considered, or by seeing her breast, which being opened that they might stop the blood, suffered none to doubt of the sex of <hi>Felicia.</hi> He was struck by that discovery as by a clap of thunder, he wanted words to express his grief and trouble, and his tears performed the office which his tongue could not. He fell on his knees before that poor dying Maid, and by doleful actions evidenced the sorrow that pierced his heart. <hi>Felicia</hi> by her carriage made appear that her thoughts were taken up about a future state, for closeing her eyes that she might not behold an object, that had alwayes been too dear to her, deprive me not, said she, by an untimely p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, of the sole happiness I can pretend to; I
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:199411:70"/> thought my self bound in Christian duty to pardon you for my Death, and to justifie injured innocence. Having satisfied that obligation, leave my mind in so much liberty, that I may perform what I owe to my self; with these words she begg'd to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to some place of retirement; and the vehemency of her discourse having made her wound bleed again afresh in so great abundance, that she was quite spent; she turned again to the Count and prayed him to be gone. He obeyed these her last orders, and came into my Chamber to see what condition I was in. He perceived that I continued still in fainting fits; and having beheld me for some time with a countenance full of grief, shame, and compassion, he went into his Closet, took out some mony, and presently got on horseback, attended only by one Servant; none of the rest daring to ask him his design. So soon as I was come to my self again, I asked for my Husband; and was informed of all that I have told you. Poor <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia</hi> died next day with all the marks
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:199411:70"/> of contrition that might give ground to hope well of her Salvation. Since that dismal day, Madam, I have worn out my life in unconceivable affliction, for to sum up my sorrows, the Man, whom the Count had taken with him, came back again, and told me that he stayed fifteen dayes for his Master at <hi>Thoulon,</hi> whither he had ordered him to go; but that having heard no news of him there, he believed he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken some other way. I spared no pains nor cost to learn intelligence of him; but seeing the hour was not yet come which should deliver me from my troubles, all my searching was in vain. You are perhaps a little curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Madam, to know what became of <hi>Madamoiselle</hi> of <hi>Freslon,</hi> who was the cause of all these strange Catastro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies you have reason to think that she was certainly touched with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion for all the calamities that she had brought upon her Family! but alas, she had not a heart that was sensible of pity; and if she had any grief, it was only because I had not met with the fate of <hi>Felicia.</hi> I understood by
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:199411:71"/> her own relation, that she had made use of the favours, that I shewed that unhappy Maid, whil'st under the name of <hi>Valantin,</hi> I took her for a person of quality, to incite her Brother to jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie; I was likewise informed that the care I had to avoid company, serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a pretext to the malice of that wicked Lady. What more shall I tell you, Madam, all things seemed to conspire for my ruine, since it is certain that the last discourse I had with the Count quite extinguished the little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that remained to him. In fine, without speaking any more of all the pains that I have suffered since that sad day, I shall only tell you that the Bishop of <hi>G.</hi> having come to see me, told me that there was an Hermit at <hi>Terrasson,</hi> who led the life of an Angel, a relation whereof he had seen in the hands of my Lady Dutchess of <hi>C.</hi> I found my self strangely moved at that discourse without being able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture the reason of it: In a word, Madam having done so many things in vain, I have at length undertaken one that, hath succeeded, I dare not
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:199411:71"/> say luckily until I know, whether or not the person, for whom I take all this pains, will be pleased to pity himself and me.</p>
               <p>This is, Madam, a true narrative of the History which my Lady <hi>Freslon</hi> told me; I thought you would take in good part that I imparted it to you, and though her relation be nothing so pleasant; as if it had been a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick adventure, such as are all that now adayes comes abroad under the title of Novels, yet I judged it so rare as that it might deserve your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when it is considered as a real story. I told that Lady that I sensibly concerned my self in all the adventures she had related to me; and the truth is I looked upon it as a miracle, to find in this our age a Lady whom conjugal love had made undertake so many things. But at length God was pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reward so exemplary virtue, for the fifth day that the Countess was at my house, as we were taking a walk in the evening, we saw at a pretty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance a Gentleman making up towards us. I did not know him at first, but
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:199411:72"/> the Countess giving a great cry, told me that she was much mistaken if it was not her Husband: when he drew a little nearer I found she was in the right. Had Heaven bestowed on me so much cloquence as our Romance makers really have, or believe they have, I might have a fair occasion to make an ample description of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of an unexpected joy; for, I think, never any felt more than that lovely Countess; she seemed so transported that I, who look not on marriage as the happiest of all other states of life, should advise all people to enter into that sacred bond, if they could often enjoy such ravishing pleasures. I do not think, Madam, that I can make use of a more significant expression to declare the happiness which these two persons enjoyed at that time; but having reflected on it a little better, I think it not ill done to dispense with pleasures that must cost so great pains, and that all things rightly considered there is no condition preferable to an absolute liberty. But I forget my self, Madam, in engageing on rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonings
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:199411:72"/> that may be tedious to you, after so long a relation; seeing time and duty do rather require, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out longer discoursing, I should with most profound respect assure you, that I am.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  <signed>Your most humble and obedient Servant. R.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>